<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two treatises the first proving both by history &amp; record that the bishops are a fundamental &amp; essential part of our English Parliament : the second that they may be judges in capital cases.</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13764404</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13764404</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101709</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66906)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101709)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1055:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two treatises the first proving both by history &amp; record that the bishops are a fundamental &amp; essential part of our English Parliament : the second that they may be judges in capital cases.</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14, [2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Braddyll for Robert Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The second treatise has special t.p. and separate paging.</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Womock.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Temporal power.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101709:1"/>
            <p>TWO TREATISES</p>
            <p>The <hi>FIRST,</hi> Proving both by HISTORY &amp; RECORD THAT THE BISHOPS ARE A <hi>Fundamental &amp; Eſſential Part</hi> OF OUR Engliſh Parliament: The <hi>SECOND,</hi> That they may be JUDGES IN <hi>Capital Caſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Braddyll</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:101709:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101709:2"/>
                  <head>THAT THE BISHOPS MAKE A FUNDAMENTAL &amp; ESSENTIAL PART OF THE <hi>Engliſh Parliament.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THough the Demerits of this Sacred Order of men is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently known and acknowledged, though their Sufferings in the late ill times are notorious to the whole world, and no leſs a Scandal to this Nation, I ſpeak of thoſe who then traiterouſly uſurped the Name and Title of the Supreme Authority of <hi>England;</hi> yet there are not ſtill wanting thoſe of the old Leaven, who endeavour to embroil us again, who ſtill raiſe and maintain the old Scruples and Jealouſies, and endeavour as much as in them lies, to put us again into the old and preternatural Ferments of 42: 'tis ſtrange you will ſay, that a Nation ſhould be twice undone by the ſame ways and method; that the evil ſucceſs we all of us felt (ſave thoſe of the <hi>Independent</hi> Faction) ſhould not deter us from endeavouring the like unſetlements for the future; I wiſh our Fears and Jealouſies were groundleſs; but ſo long as the old and baffled Arguments are rallied by ſuch men, ſo long as they proceed to make ill uſe of the Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of their Prince and his Government under whom they live in peace, and endeavour to unravel the Conſtitutions of our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, hereby to bring us into the Diſorders under which we ſo late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly groaned, and out of which, by the goodneſs of God, we are now in ſafety eſcaped, it will not (I hope) be thought unſeaſonable to any perſon who is a Friend to his Prince or Country, or to himſelf in his own quiet and ſettlement which he now enjoyes, to mind and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him (I hope 'tis no ill counſel) <hi>ſtare ſuper vias antiquas, to tread in and keep to the old paths. Regia via eſt tuta via; the Kings way is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and beſt of ways.</hi> Let us then in the Name of God ſee what were the ancient uſages, the old Conſtitutions under which we and our Forefathers were happy, our ancient Kingdom ſo famous throughout the whole Civiliz'd World, hath flouriſhed, and become ſo renown'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101709:3"/> as erſt it hath been: And ſeeing a great Queſtion hath of late, and is now again raiſed concerning the Sacred Order of Biſhops, as to their Right of being and voting in our Parliaments, we ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to evince and prove this great Point, which 'tis hoped may in a good meaſure contribute to the allaying the heats of this ſort of men amongſt us, and who ſeem to be the moſt buſie and forward in theſe Embroylments. And that we may the more orderly and methodically proceed to evince what we have undertaken, and in regard this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is about the very Conſtitution of our Government, we can, I think, do no better than to make uſe herein of the good old Maxim and Rule <hi>de Legibus &amp; longa conſuetudine. Si de interpretatione Legis quaeritur, inprimis inſpiciendum eſt, quo jure Civitas retro in hujuſmodi caſibus uſa fuerit: Conſuetudo enim optima interpretatio Legis est. If you would know the true ſence and interpretation of any Law, you must eſpecially look to the practice and uſage of the Law; for that Cuſtom is the beſt interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law.</hi> We now ſeem (at leaſt ſome party amongſt us) to queſtion whether our Biſhops are an Eſſential part of the Parliament; which, together with His Majeſty, as to the Enacting of Laws, and giving of Aids and Subſidies, is the old Government under which <hi>England</hi> hath heretofore to the envy of our Neighbours, flouriſh'd and been happy.<hi>—Foelices nimium bona ſi ſua norant Angli.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That we may then (I ſay) put this Queſtion out of queſtion, we ſhall endeavour to prove by two ſorts of Arguments; of which one ſhall be <hi>De Jure,</hi> and the other <hi>De Facto:</hi> the one derived from that Original Right which is veſted in them; the other from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Exerciſe and continual practice by which that Right hath been enjoyed in all times foregoing.</p>
                  <p>And firſt we ſhall begin with the proofs <hi>de jure,</hi> and therein firſt with that which doth occur in the Laws of King <hi>Athelston,</hi> one of the firſt Monarchs of the Engliſh Saxons. Among which there is a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (it is <hi>chap.</hi> 11.) entituled <hi>De officio Epiſcopi &amp; quid pertinet ad offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium ejus;</hi> that is to ſay, Touching the office of a Biſhop, and that which doth of right belong unto it. In which Chapter it is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>viz. Epiſcopo jure pertinet omnem rectitudinem promovere, Dei ſcilicet &amp; ſeculi &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Spelm. Counſ p.</hi> 402.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; convenit ut per conſilium &amp; teſtimonium ejus omne Legis ſcitum, &amp; Burgi menſura, &amp; omne pondus ſit ſecundum dicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem ejus inſtitutum;</hi> that is to ſay, it belongeth of right unto the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> to promote Juſtice in matters which concern both the Church and State, and unto him it appertaineth, that by his Counſel and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, all Laws, and Weights, and Meaſures, be ordained through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>2. Next we will have recourſe to the old <hi>Record</hi> entituled, <hi>Modus tenendi Parliamentum;</hi> In which it is affirmed, <hi>Ad Parliamentum Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniri &amp; venire debere</hi> Archiepiſcopos, Epiſcopos, <hi>Abbates, Priores, &amp; alios majores</hi> Cleri, <hi>qui tenent per Comitatum aut Baroniam ratione hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſ modi tenurae;</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">Modus tenendi Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentum.</note> That all the <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbats, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors,</hi> and other <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church, who hold their Lands either by an <hi>Earls</hi> Fee, or a <hi>Barons</hi> Fee, were to be ſummoned, and come to <hi>Parliament</hi> in regard of their Tenure.</p>
                  <p>3. Next, look we on the Chartularies of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognized
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101709:3"/> in full Parliament at <hi>Clarendon,</hi> under <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, where they are called <hi>Avitas conſuetudines,</hi> which declare it thus, <hi>Archiepiſcopi, Epiſcopi, &amp; univerſae Perſonae qui de Rege tenent in capite, habeant poſſeſſiones ſuas de Rege ſic ut Baroniam, &amp;c. Et ſicut caeteri Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes debent intereſſe judiciis Curiae Regis cum Baronibus, quouſque pervenerit ad diminutionem membrorum vel ad mortem</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Math. Paris in H.</hi> 2.</note> The meaning is in brief, that <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and all other Eccleſiaſtical Perſons which hold in <hi>Capite</hi> of the King, are to have and hold their Lands in <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and that they ought as Barons</hi> to be preſent in all Judgments with the other <hi>Barons</hi> in the Court of <hi>Parl.</hi> untill the very Sentence of Death or Mutilation (which was very common in thoſe times) was to be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And then they commonly did uſe to withdraw themſelves, not out of any incapacity ſuppoſed to be in them by the Law of <hi>Engl.</hi> but out of a reſtraint impos'd upon them by the Can. of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4. In the <hi>Great Charter</hi> made by King <hi>John,</hi> in the laſt of his Reign, we have the form of ſummoning a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and calling thoſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who have Votes therein, thus expreſſed at large. <hi>Ad haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum commune concilium Regni de auxilio aſſidendo, &amp;c. Et de ſcutagiis aſſidendis, faciemus ſummoneri Archiepiſc. Abbates, Comites, &amp; majores Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones Regni ſigillatim per literas noſtras, &amp; praeterea ſummoneri faciemus in generali per Vice-Com. &amp; Ballivos noſtros omnes alios qui in Capite tenent ad certum diem, ſcil. ad terminum</hi> 40 <hi>dierum ad minus, &amp; ad certum locum, &amp;c.</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">Id. in Job.</note> In which we have not only a moſt evident Proof, that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are of right to be called to <hi>Parliament,</hi> for granting <hi>Subſidies</hi> and <hi>Eſcuage,</hi> and treating of the great Affairs which concern the Kingdom, but that they are to be ſummoned by particular Letters, as well as the <hi>Earls</hi> &amp; <hi>Barons,</hi> or either of them; A form or copy of which Summons iſſued in the time of the ſaid King <hi>John,</hi> is extant on Record, and put in Print not many <note place="margin">(*) <hi>P.</hi> 1. 20. 5.</note> years ſince in the Titles of Honour.</p>
                  <p>5. We have it thus in the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3<hi>d.</hi> the Birthright of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subject, according as it ſtands tranſlated in the Book of Statutes. <hi>Firſt we have granted to God, and by this our preſent Charters have confirmed for us, and our Heirs for ever, That the</hi> Church of England <hi>ſhall be free, and ſhall enjoy all her whole</hi> Rights and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>inviolable,</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Magna Charta c.</hi> 1.</note> But it is a known <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that all the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and many of the greater <hi>Clergy</hi> (and peradventure alſo the <hi>Inferior Clergy</hi> in the ſaid Kings time) had their <hi>Votes</hi> in <hi>Parliament;</hi> and therefore is to be preſerved <hi>inviolable</hi> by the Kings of <hi>England, their Heirs and Succeſſors for ever.</hi> Which Charter, as it was confirmed by a Curſe denounced on all the Infringers of it, by <hi>Boniface</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Math. Par. in H.</hi> 3.</note> and ratified, in no fewer than 80. ſuceedings Parliaments: So was it Enacted in the Reign of <hi>Hdward</hi> the firſt, That <hi>it ſhould be ſent under the great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>to all the Cathedral Churches of the Kingdom, to be read twice a year</hi> before the People; (†) That they ſhould be ready four times a year in a full County Court, <note n="(*)" place="margin">28 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> and finally that <hi>all Judgments given againſt it ſhould</hi> be void and null; <note n="(†)" place="margin">28 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> the Application of which laſt Clauſe I refer to thoſe, to whom the rectifiing of the Error (which to the contrary thereof hath been committed) doth of right belong. <note place="margin">(*) 28 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>6. We have the Proteſtation of <hi>John Stratford</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 3<hi>d.</hi> who being in disfavour with
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101709:4"/> the King, and denied entrance into the Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> challenged his Place, and Suffrage there, as the firſt <hi>Peer of the Realm,</hi> and One that <hi>ought to have the firſt voice in</hi> Parliament in right of his See.</p>
                  <p>But hear him ſpeak his own words, which are theſe that follow, <hi>Amici</hi> (for he ſpake to thoſe that took witneſs of it) <hi>Rex me ad hoc Parliamentum ſcripto ſuo vocavit, &amp; ego tanquam</hi> major par Regni <hi>poſt Regem,</hi> &amp; primam voce habere debens <hi>in Parliamento,</hi> jura Eccleſiae meae Cantuarienſis <hi>vendico &amp; ideo ingreſſum in</hi> Parliamento peto <note n="(†)" place="margin">Antiqui. Brit. in Gati. Stratford.</note> which makes it plain enough, that the Arch-Biſhop did not challenge a place in Parliament, as the firſt Peer of the Realm, either by way of favour, or cuſtom only, but as a power and priviledge as he ought to have <hi>(habere debent</hi> are the words) in the Right of his See.</p>
                  <p>7. And laſtly, there is the proteſtation on Record, of all the Biſhops in the Reign of King <hi>Richard</hi> the 2<hi>d.</hi> at what time <hi>William Courtney</hi> was Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury:</hi> who being to withdraw themſelves from the Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> at the pronouncing of the Sentence of Death on ſome guilty Lords, firſt made their <hi>Procurators</hi> to ſupply their rooms, and then put up their <hi>Proteſtations</hi> to preſerve their Rights; the ſum whereof, for as much as doth concern this buſineſs in their own words thus; De jure, &amp; conſuetudine <hi>Regni</hi> Angliae <hi>ad Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopum</hi> Cantuarienſem, <hi>qui pro tempore fuerit, nec non caeteros</hi> Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganos, <hi>confratres, &amp; compatres, Abbates &amp; Priores, alioſque Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latos quoſcunque per</hi> Baroniam <hi>de Domino Rege tenentes,</hi> Pertinet, <hi>in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentis Regis quibuscunque,</hi> ut Pares <hi>Regni praedicti perſonaliter intereſſe ibidemque de</hi> Regni negotiis, <hi>ac aliis tractari conſuetis cum caeteris dicti Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> paribus, <hi>&amp; aliis ibidem</hi> jus intereſſendi <hi>habentibus Conſulere, &amp; Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctare, Ordinare, Statuere, &amp; Definire, ac caetera facere quae Parliamento ibidem imminent facienda.</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">In vita Gu. Courtney</note> It appertains ſay they, both by Right and Cuſtom to the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> for the time being, as alſo unto all the reſt of his Compeers, as well as the Suffragan Biſhops, as to the Abbots, Priors and other Prelates whatſoever, which hold their Land by <hi>Barony</hi> of our Lord the King, to be perſonally preſent at all Parliaments as <hi>Peers of the Realm,</hi> and there together with the reſt of the Peers, and all other, which have Right to be therein preſent to Conſult, treat of, and Ordain, and finally to determine and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh all ſuch things, and matters, as are accuſtomably handled, and ordained in Parliaments. Which ſets the matter as I take it beyond all diſpute, as to the firſt of theſe two heads, or ſorts of Arguments, whereby I was to prove this point, which were thoſe <hi>de jure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us next ſee whether this <hi>Right</hi> of theirs be confirmed and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced by continual practice, and that they have not loſt it by <hi>Diſcontinuance;</hi> which is my ſecond kind of Argument, thoſe I mean <hi>de facto.</hi> And in this way of proof, we can go as high, as the firſt preaching of the Goſpel to the <hi>Engliſh Saxons,</hi> and ſo deſcend unto thoſe laſt times without interruption. By which it will appear, that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity in this Nation, and the Biſhops Votes in Parliaments, and Common Councils, are of like Antiquity.</p>
                  <p>For firſt, no ſooner had King <hi>Ethelbert</hi> received the Goſpel, but preſently we read, that as well the <hi>Clergy,</hi> as the <hi>Laity,</hi> were ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to the Common Council: which the <hi>Saxons</hi> ſometimes called
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101709:4"/> 
                     <hi>Mycell Synoth,</hi> the great Aſſembly, and ſometimes <hi>Witennegemote,</hi> the Councel or Aſſembly of the Wiſe men of the Realm, <hi>Anno</hi> 605. <hi>Ethelbertus Rex in fide corroboratus Catholica,</hi> &amp;c. Cantuariae <hi>convocavit Commune Conſilium tam</hi> Cleri, <hi>quam</hi> Populi; King <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>H. Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Conc. p.</hi> 116.</note> 
                     <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> as my Author hath it, being confirmed in the Faith in the year 605. (which was but nine years after his Converſion) together with <hi>Berha</hi> his Queen, their Son <hi>Thalbald,</hi> the Reverend Archbiſhop <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and all the reſt of the Nobility, did ſolemnize the Feaſt of Chriſts Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the City of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> and did there cauſe to be aſſembled on the 9th. of <hi>January,</hi> the <hi>Common Council</hi> of his Kingdom, as well the Clergy, as the Lay-Subject; by whoſe Conſent and Approbation he cauſed the Monaſtery by him built, to be dedicated to the honour of God Almighty, by the hand of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And though no queſtion other Examples of this kind may be found amongſt the <hi>Saxon Heptarchies,</hi> yet being the <hi>Weſt Saxon</hi> Kingdom did in fine prevail, and united all the reſt into one <hi>Monarchy,</hi> we ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves unto that more punctually and with greater care.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. And firſt we read of <hi>Egbert,</hi> who firſt united the ſeven King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the <hi>Saxons</hi> under the common name of <hi>England,</hi> that he cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be convened at <hi>London</hi> his Biſhops, and the Peers of the higheſt Rank, <hi>pro conſilio capiendo adverſus Danicos Pyratas,</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">Charta Whitlagii Mercyorum Regis ap. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulph.</note> to adviſe upon ſome courſe againſt the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Pyrates, who infeſted the Sea-coaſt of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. Another Parliament or Council (call it which you will) called at <hi>Kingbury, Anno</hi> 855, in the time of <hi>Ethelwolph,</hi> the Son of <hi>Egbert, pro negotiis Regni,</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">Charta Bertult mer. Regis ap. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulf.</note> to treat of the Affairs of the Kingdom; the Acts whereof are ratified and ſubſcribed by the <hi>Biſhops, Abbots,</hi> and other great men of the Realm.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. We find that the ſame King <hi>Ethelwolph</hi> in a Parliament, or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of his States at <hi>Wincheſter, Anno</hi> 855. <hi>Cum conſilio Epiſcoporum &amp; Principum,</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">Ingulf. Croyland. hiſt</note> by the Advice and Counſel of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, confirmed unto the <hi>Clergy</hi> the tenth part of all mens Goods, and ordered that the Tythe ſo confirmed unto them ſhould be free <hi>ab omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſecularibus Servitutibus,</hi> from all ſecular Services and Impoſitions.</p>
                  <p n="4">IV. The two Charters were iſſued out by <hi>Athelſtone</hi> above-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Conſilio Wifelmi Archiepiſcopi mei, &amp; aliorum Epiſcoporum meorum,</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ap. eund. p.</hi> 402, 403.</note> by the advice of <hi>Wiſelme</hi> his Archbiſhop, and his other Biſhops.</p>
                  <p>And V. That <hi>Ina</hi> in the year 902. cauſed the great Council of his Realm to be Aſſembled, conſiſting <hi>ex Epiſcopis, Principibus, Proceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> &amp;c. of Biſhops, Princes, Nobles, Earls, and of all the wiſe men, Elders, and people of the whole Kingdom, and there Enacted divers Laws for the weal of this Realm. <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ap. eund. p,</hi> 219.</note> We alſo read this in the Reign of <hi>Edrid,</hi> Anno 948. <hi>viz. in feſto igitur Nativitatis</hi> Beatae Mariae <hi>cum univerſi Magnates Regni per Regium Edictum ſummoniti, tam</hi> Archiepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi <hi>&amp;</hi> Epiſcopi, <hi>ac</hi> Abbates, <hi>quam caeteri totius Regni Proceres &amp; Optima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> Londini <hi>conveniſſent ad tractandum de negotiis publicis totius Regni;</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Id. ibid. p.</hi> 497. <hi>edit. Lond.</hi>
                     </note> That in the Feaſt of the Nativity of the Bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> the great men of the Realm, that is to ſay, <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Peers, were ſummoned by the Kings Writ to appear at <hi>London,</hi> to handle and conclude about the publick Affairs of the Kingdom.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101709:5"/> Mention of which Aſſembly is made again at the Foundation and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment of the Abbey of <hi>Crowland;</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mad p.</hi> 500.</note> and afterwards a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame by <hi>Edgar,</hi> Anno 966. <hi>Praeſentibus Archiepiſcopis, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopis, Abbatibus, &amp; Optimatibus Regni;</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Id. p.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 1. 50.</note> In the preſence of <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots,</hi> and Peers of the Realm. The like Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Eſtates</hi> we find to have been called by <hi>Canutus</hi> the <hi>Dane,</hi> after the death of <hi>Edm. Ironſide,</hi> for the ſetling of the Crown on his own head, of which thus the Author, <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rog. Hoved. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pag. pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or p.</hi> 250.</note> 
                     <hi>Cujus poſt mortem Rex</hi> Canutus <hi>omnes</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopos, <hi>&amp; Duces, nec non &amp; Principes, cunctoſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Optimates gentis</hi> Angliae, Londini <hi>congregari juſſit.</hi> Where we ſtill find the <hi>Biſhops</hi> to be called to <hi>Parliament,</hi> as well as the Dukes, Princes, and the reſt of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and to be ranked and marſhalled firſt (which clearly ſhews that they were always reckoned for the <hi>firſt Eſtate)</hi> before the greateſt and moſt eminent of the <hi>Secular</hi> Peers. And ſo we find it alſo in a Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> the laſt King of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Race) by which he granted certain Lands and Priviledges to the Church of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> An. 1066. <hi>Cum Concilio &amp; Decreto</hi> Archiepiſcoporum, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcoporum, <hi>Comitum, aliorum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Optimatum;</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>ap. H. Spel. in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. p.</hi> 630.</note> with the Counſel and Decree of the <hi>Arch-biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> Earls, and others of his Nobles. And all this while the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and other Prelates of the Church did hold by no other Tenure than <hi>in pura &amp; perpetua Eleemoſyna;</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">Camden in Brit.</note> or <hi>frank Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moygne,</hi> as our Lawyers call it; and therefore ſate in <hi>Parliament</hi> in no other capacity than as <hi>Spiritual</hi> perſons meerly; who by their extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orinary knowledge in the Word of God, and in ſuch other parts of Learning as the world then knew, were thought beſt able to direct and adviſe their Princes in all points of difficulty. But when the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueror had poſſeſt the State, then the caſe was altered. The <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church were no longer ſuffered to hold their Land in <hi>Frank Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moigne,</hi> as before they did, or to be free from Secular Services and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, as before they were. Although they kept their Lands, yet they changed their <hi>Tenure,</hi> and by the Conqueror were ordained to hold their Lands <hi>ſub militari ſervitute,</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in Will.</hi> 1. <hi>An.</hi> 1070.</note> either in <hi>Capite,</hi> or by <hi>Baronage,</hi> or ſome ſuch <hi>military</hi> hold, and thereby were compellable to aid the King in all times of War, with Men, Arms, and Horſes, as the Lay-Subjects of the ſame <hi>Tenures</hi> were required to do.</p>
                  <p>Which though it were conceived to be a great <hi>Disfranchiſement</hi> at firſt, and an heavy burden to the <hi>Prelacy,</hi> yet it conduced at laſt to their <hi>greater honour,</hi> in giving them a <hi>further Title to their Place in Parliament,</hi> than that which formerly they could pretend to. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they claimed a place therein <hi>ratione Officii,</hi> only by reaſon of their <hi>Offices,</hi> or <hi>Spiritual</hi> Dignities; but after this, by reaſon alſo of thoſe <hi>Baronies,</hi> which were erected, and annexed to their ſeveral Dignities; <hi>En reſpect de leur poſſeſſions l'antient Baronies annexes a leur Dignities</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Stratford Pleas. l.</hi> 3.</note> as our Lawyers have it. From this time forwards we muſt look upon them in the Houſe of <hi>Parliament,</hi> not as <hi>Biſhops</hi> only, but as <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> of the <hi>Realm</hi> alſo; and ſo themſelves affirmed to the <hi>Temporal</hi> Lords in the <hi>Parliament</hi> holden at <hi>Northampton,</hi> under <hi>Henry</hi> the Second. <hi>Non ſedemus hic</hi> Epiſcopi, <hi>ſed</hi> Barones, <hi>Pares hic ſumus:</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Selden titles of hon. p</hi> 2. 18.</note> We ſit not here, ſay they, as <hi>Biſhops</hi> only, but as <hi>Barons;</hi> we are <hi>Barons,</hi> and you are <hi>Barons;</hi> here we ſit as <hi>Peers.</hi> Which laſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101709:5"/> is alſo verified in <hi>terminis,</hi> by the words of a Statute, or Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, wherein the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are acknowledged to be <hi>Peers of the Land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to proceed more particularly to our proofs <hi>de facto,</hi> after the alteration of their Tenures by the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueror; we find a Parliament aſſembled in the fifth year of that King, wherein are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Epiſcopi, Abbates, Comites, &amp; Primates totius Angliae,</hi> (†) the <note place="margin">(*) <hi>Math. Paris in Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li elmo</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Abbots Earls, and the reſt of the Baronage of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>3ly.</hi> In the ninth year of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> an old Author telleth us, <hi>de Regni ſtatu acturus,</hi> Epiſcopos, <hi>Abbates, &amp; quoſcunque Regni Proceres in unum praecepti ſui ſanctione egit,</hi> that being to conſult of the Affairs of the Kingdom, he called together by his Writ the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Abbots and all the Peers of the Realm, <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Edmor hiſt. Mov. l.</hi> 2.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>2ly.</hi> During the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, for we will take but one example out of each Kings Reign, though each Kings Reign would yeild us more) a <hi>Parliament</hi> was called at <hi>London.</hi> wherein were many things diſpatched, aa well of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> as Secular na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and Abbots being preſent with the other Lords; <hi>Coacto apud</hi> Londinium <hi>Magno</hi> Epiſcoporum <hi>&amp; Procerum, Abbatum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que concilio,</hi> multa Eccleſiaſticarum, &amp; Secularium rerum ordinata negotia, deciſa Litigia, ſaith the Monk of <hi>Malmsbury</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Malmbs. Hiſt. Reg. Ang. l.</hi> 5.</note> and of this <hi>Parliament</hi> it is, I take it, that <hi>Edmor</hi> ſpeaketh <hi>Hist. Novel. l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 91.</p>
                  <p>Proceed we <hi>4ly.</hi> to King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond (for King <hi>Stephens</hi> Reign was ſo full of Wars and Tumults, that there is very little to be found of <hi>Parliaments)</hi> and there we find the <hi>Biſhops</hi> with the other <hi>Peers,</hi> convened in Parliament for the determination of the points in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy between <hi>Alphonſo</hi> King of <hi>Castile</hi> and <hi>Sancho</hi> King of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varre,</hi> referred by com-promiſe to the King of <hi>England,</hi> and here determined by King <hi>Henry</hi> amongſt other things. <hi>Habito cum</hi> Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, <hi>Comitibus &amp; Baronibus</hi> cum deliberatione <hi>Conſilio,</hi> as in <hi>Roger Hoveden</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoveden. Annal. pac. Roſe in H.</hi> 2.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>5ly.</hi> Next time comes <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, his Son; during whoſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment by the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> his Brother <hi>John</hi> then Earl of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riton,</hi> endeavoured by force and cunning in <hi>Normandy</hi> to ſet the Crown on his own head; which cauſed <hi>Hubert</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> to call a Parliament <hi>(Convocatis coram eo Epiſcopis, Comitibus &amp; Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Regni,</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">Id. in Ioh.</note> wherein the Biſhops, Earls, and Barons, did with one conſent agree to ſeize on his Eſtate, and ſuppreſs his power, the better to preſerve the Kingdom in Wealth, Peace, and Safety.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>6ly.</hi> After ſucceeded <hi>John,</hi> and he calls a <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein were certain Laws made for the defence of this Kingdom, <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni aſſenſu</hi> Archiepiſcoporum, Epiſcoporum, <hi>Comitum, Baronum &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium fidelium ſuorum Angliae,</hi> by the Common Counſel and Aſſent of the <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> Earls, Barons, and the reſt of his Lieges. (Remember what was ſaid before touching the Writ of Summons in the ſaid Kings time) from this time till the laſt <hi>Parliament</hi> of King <hi>Charles,</hi> there is no Kings Reign of which we have not many, (though not all) the Acts of Parliament ſtill it Print amongſt us. Nor is there any Act of Parliament in the Printed Books, to the Enacting of which the Biſhops Approbation and Conſent is not plainly ſpecified, either in the general <hi>Proem</hi> ſet before the Acts, or in the Body of the Acts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101709:6"/> themſelves, as by the Books themſelves doth at large appear.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>7ly.</hi> And to this kind of proof may be further added the Form and manner of the Writ, by which the Prelates in all times have been called to Parliament, being the very Law <hi>Verbatim,</hi> with that which is directed to the Temporal Barons, ſave that the Spiritual Lords are commanded to attend the Service, <hi>in fide &amp; dilectione,</hi> the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>in fide &amp; Homagio,</hi> and of late times <hi>in fide &amp; Ligeantia quibus nobis tenemini.</hi> A Form or Copy of which Summons as ancient as King <hi>John</hi>'s time, is ſtill reſerved upon Record, directed <hi>Nominatim</hi> to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Titles of Hon. part</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> and then a <hi>Scriptum eſt ſimiliter</hi> to the reſidue of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Abbots, Earls and Barons. Then add the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege</hi> of Parliament for themſelves and their Servants, during the time of the Seſſions, the Liberty to <hi>kill and take one or two of the Kings Deer, as they paſs by any of his Forests in coming to</hi> Parliament <hi>upon his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment,</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">Charta de foreſt. cap.</note> their enjoying of the ſame Immunities, which are and have been heretofore enjoyed by the <hi>Temporal</hi> Barons; <note n="(†)" place="margin">Camden in Briiania.</note> and tell me if the Biſhops did not ſit in <hi>Parliament</hi> by as good a Title as the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Lords, and therefore <hi>Eſſential, Fundamental</hi> parts of the Court of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>By this Diſcourſe it may appear, that the Biſhops Sit and Vote in Parliament by a double capacity; as Biſhops, firſt in reference to their ſeveral Sees; and ſecondly, as <hi>Peers,</hi> in regard of their <hi>Baronies.</hi> In both reſpects accounted one of the <hi>Three Eſtates,</hi> and the <hi>firſt alſo of the Three,</hi> as from the Premiſes may be gathered without any great trouble. But in ſo nice a point as this, we ſhall not only build upon general <hi>Inferences,</hi> but particular <hi>Evidences.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And firſt it is affirmed by <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> in his Relation of the Life and Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 5th, <hi>That when his Funerals were ended, the three Estates of the Realm of</hi> England <hi>did aſſemble together, and declare his Son King</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 6th. <hi>being an Infant of</hi> 8 <hi>Months old, to be their Sovereign Lord,</hi> (†) as his Heir and Succeſſor. And <hi>three Eſtates</hi> there <note place="margin">(*) <hi>Tit. Liv. M. S. in Bib. Bodl.</hi>
                     </note> could not be to perform that Service, unleſs the Biſhops were acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be one of the number.</p>
                  <p>2ly, <hi>In the Parliament Rolls of King</hi> Richard <hi>the third, there is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Bill or Parchment preſented to that Prince, being then Duke of</hi> Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter, <hi>on the behalf, and in the Name of the</hi> Three Eſtates <hi>of the Realm of</hi> England, <hi>that is to wit, the</hi> Lords Spiritual <hi>and</hi> Temporal, <hi>and of the</hi> Commons <hi>by name; which foraſmuch as neither the ſaid</hi> Three Eſtates, <hi>nor the perſons which delivered it on their behalf, were then aſſembled in form of Parliament, was afterwards in the firſt Parliament of that King, by the ſame</hi> Three Eſtates <hi>Aſſembled in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> (I ſpeak the very words of the Act it ſelf) <hi>and by Authority of the ſame Enrolled, Recorded, and Approved;</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>An. Speed in K. R.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>and at the request and by the aſſent of the</hi> Three Eſtates <hi>of this Realm, that is to ſay, the Lords</hi> Spiritual <hi>and</hi> Temporal, <hi>and</hi> Commons <hi>of this Land Aſſembled in this preſent Parliament, and by Authority of the ſame it be pronounced, decreed, and declared, that our ſaid Sovereign Lord the King was and is the very and undoubted Heir of this Realm of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101709:6"/>
                  <p> And 3ly, So it is acknowledged in a (†) Statute of 1 <hi>El.</hi> c. 3. where <note place="margin">1 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 3</note> the Lords <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal, and the Commons in that Parliament aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled,</hi> being ſaid expreſly and <hi>in terminis</hi> to repreſent the <hi>three Eſtates</hi> of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> did recognize the Queens <hi>Majeſty to be their True, Lawful, and undoubted Sovereign Lieg'd Lady and Queen.</hi> And in a Statute of the 8th. year of the ſaid Queens Reign, the Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy are declared to be the <hi>greatest Eſtates of the Realm,</hi> and called the <hi>High Eſtate of Prelacy,</hi> in another place.</p>
                  <p>It may perhaps be thought unneceſſary or impertinent, to add the Teſtimony and Authority of a private perſon to that which hath been ſaid by our Laws and Statutes. But being it is ſuch a Perſon as was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for the Oracle of the Law when he ſerved in Parliament, his Judgment may be taken for a creditable and ſufficient Evidence in the preſent Caſe. It is the Teſtimony and Authority of Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> ſucceſſively Chief Juſtice of either Bench; who in his Book <hi>Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Jurisdiction of Courts,</hi> ſpeaks thus of Parliaments, <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Coke of Parl. fol.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>This Court</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>conſiſteth of the Kings Majeſty ſitting there as in his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Politick Capacity, and of the Three Eſtates of the Realm,</hi> viz. <hi>of the Lords Spiritual,</hi> Archbiſhops <hi>and</hi> Biſhops, <hi>who ſit there by Succeſſion in reſpect of their Counties, Baronies, parcel of their Biſhopricks which they hold alſo in their Politick Capacity; and every one of theſe when any Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be holden, ought</hi> ex debito Juſtitiae <hi>to have a Writ of Summons. Secondly, The Lords Temporal, Dukes, Marqueſſes, Earls, Viſcounts and Barons, who ſit there by reaſon of their Dignities, which they hold by Deſcent or Creation, and likewiſe every one of theſe being of full age, ought to have a Writ of Summons</hi> ex debito Juſtitiae. <hi>The Third</hi> Eſtate <hi>is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Realm, whereof there be Knights of Shires or Counties, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of Cities, and Burgeſſes of Burghs. All which are reſpectively Elected by the Shires or Counties, Cities and Burroughs, by force of the Kings Writ</hi> ex debito Juſtitiae, <hi>and none of them ought to be omitted: And theſe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all the Commons of the whole Realm, and are truſted for them.</hi> So He: and this is plain enough beyond exception.</p>
                  <p>Add hereunto <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> that in all Chriſtian Kingdoms of the <hi>Gothick Model,</hi> there are no more nor fewer than three Eſtates, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented at the Will and Pleaſure of the Supreme Prince, for their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and advice in Affairs of conſequence; that is to ſay, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and other Eccleſiaſtical perſons, who are alwayes one, the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> for themſelves, and the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> for the <hi>Commons</hi> of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Provinces;</hi> for ſo we find it in the Conſtitutions of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and the Realms of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Kingdoms of <hi>France, Poland, Hungary,</hi> together with thoſe of <hi>Denmark, Sweden,</hi> and the Realm of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And it were ſtrange if in the Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh Parliaments,</hi> or <hi>Conventus Ordinum,</hi> the Biſhops ſhould have been left out, and none at all elected to preſent the <hi>Clergy.</hi> But being admitted with the reſt in thoſe publick Meetings, and being looked on as the <hi>First Eſtate</hi> in the <hi>Stile</hi> of that <hi>Court,</hi> it muſt needs be, that their <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion</hi> ſhakes the very <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> and makes the whole <hi>Body</hi> to be maimed and mutilated for want of ſuch a <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Member,</hi> ſo neceſſary to the making up of the whole <hi>Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101709:7"/>
                  <p> But againſt all this it is objected, firſt, that ſome Acts have paſſed in <hi>Parliament,</hi> to which the <hi>Prelates</hi> did not <hi>Vote,</hi> nor could be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Houſe when the Bill was paſſed; as in the ſentencing to death or mutilation of a guilty Perſon: as doth appear by the Laws and Conſtitutions recognized at <hi>Clarendon,</hi> and the following practice. This hath been touched on before, and we told you then, that this reſtraint was laid upon them, not by the common Law of <hi>England,</hi> or any <hi>Act</hi> or Ordinance of the Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> by which they were diſabled to attend that ſervice. It was their own voluntary Act, none compelled them to it, but only out of a conformity to ſome former Canons, <hi>ad Sanctorum Canonum inſtituta,</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">Antiqui. Brit. in Gul. Courtney.</note> (as their own words are) by which it was not lawful for the <hi>Clergy Men,</hi> to be either Judges or Aſſeſſors <hi>in cauſa ſanguinis</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Conſtitut. Othob. Fol.</hi> 45.</note>. And yet they took ſuch care to preſerve their Intereſt, that they did not only give their <hi>Proxies</hi> for there preſenting of their Perſons, but did put up their proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with a <hi>ſalvo jure,</hi> for the preſerving of their Rights for the time to come: <hi>Jure</hi> Paritatis <hi>&amp; intereſſendi in dicto Parliamento</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">Antiqu. Brit. in Gul. Courtney.</note> 
                     <hi>quoad omnia &amp; ſingula ibi exercendi in omnibus ſemper ſalvo,</hi> as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was; Examples of which are as full and frequent, as their withdrawing themſelves on the ſaid occaſions.</p>
                  <p>But then the main Objection is, that as ſome <hi>Acts</hi> have paſſed in <hi>Parliament, abſentibus Prelatis,</hi> when the Biſhops did abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their own accord; ſo many things have been tranſacted in the Parliament <hi>Excluſo Clero,</hi> when the Clergy had been exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or put out of the Houſe by ſome <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Ordinance.</hi> A <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident</hi> for this hath been found and publiſhed by ſuch as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied that poor remnant of the Churches honour: though poſſibly they will find themſelves deceived in their greateſt hopes, and yet the evidence will not ſerve to evince the cauſe. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Pamphlet entituled, <hi>the Prerogative and practice of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,</hi> firſt lays this <hi>Tenet</hi> for his ground, That many good <hi>Acts</hi> of Parliament may be made, though the <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſhould not conſent unto them (†) (which is a point <note place="margin">(*) <hi>Printed at Lond,</hi> 1628 <hi>p.</hi> 31.</note> that no man doubts of, conſidering how eaſily their <hi>Negative</hi> may be over-ruled by the far greater number of the Secular <hi>Peers.)</hi> Then he adds that in a Parliament held at St. <hi>Edmundsbury,</hi> 1196. in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, a Statute was made by the King, the Barons, and the Commons, <hi>excluſo Clero,</hi> and for the proof hereof refers us unto Biſhop <hi>Jewel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now Biſhop <hi>Jewill</hi> ſaith indeed, <q>That in a Parliament <hi>held at St.</hi> Edmundsbury <hi>by King</hi> Edward <hi>the firſt,</hi> Anno 1296. <hi>the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Biſhops were quite ſhut forth, and yet the Parliament held, and good and wholſome Laws were there Enacted, the departing or abſence of the Lords</hi> Spiritual <hi>notwithſtanding.</hi> 
                        <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                           <hi>Defence of the Apol. part</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 2. S. 1.</note>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>In the Records whereof it is written thus,</hi> Habito Rex cum Baronibus ſuis Parliamento, &amp; Clero exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, ſtatutum eſt, &amp;c. <hi>The King keeping the Parliament with his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, the Clergy, (that is to ſay, the</hi> Archbiſhops, <hi>and</hi> Biſhops,) <hi>being ſhut forth, it was enacted,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wherein who doth not ſee, if he hath</hi> any eyes, that by this reaſon, (if the proof be good)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101709:7"/> many good <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> may be made, though the <hi>Commons</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of abſence or oppoſition ſhould not conſent unto the ſame; of whoſe conſent unto that <hi>Statute</hi> (whoſoever it was) there is <hi>as little</hi> to be found in that <hi>Record,</hi> as the concurrence of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> But for anſwer unto ſo much of this <hi>Record</hi> ſo often ſpoke of, and applauded, as concerns the Biſhops, we ſay, that this (if it be truly ſenced, as I think it is not) was the particular Act of an <hi>Angry</hi> and <hi>Offended</hi> King againſt his <hi>Clergy,</hi> not to be drawn into example as a proof or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt a moſt <hi>clear, known</hi> and <hi>undoubted</hi> Right.</p>
                  <p>The Cauſe ſtood thus, A Conſtitution had been made by <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8th, <hi>Ne aliqua collecta ex eccleſiaſticis proventibus Regi, aut cuivis alii Principi concedatur;</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Math. Weſt. in E.</hi> 1.</note> that <hi>Clergy-men</hi> ſhould not pay any Tax or Tallage unto Kings or Princes out of their Spiritual Preferments without the leave of the <hi>Pope.</hi> Under pretence whereof, the <hi>Clergy</hi> at this Parliament at St. <hi>Edmonsbury,</hi> refuſed to be contributary to the Kings occaſions, when the <hi>Lay-Members</hi> of the Houſe had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in it. The King being herewith much offended, gives them a further Day to conſider of it, <hi>Adjourning</hi> the Parliament to <hi>London,</hi> there to begin on the morrow after St. <hi>Hilaries</hi> Day; and in the mean time commanded all their <hi>Barns</hi> to be faſt <hi>ſealed up.</hi> The day being come, and the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſtill perſiſting in their former obſtinacy, <hi>Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo è Parliamento Clero Conſilium Rex cum ſolis</hi> Baronibus <hi>&amp; populo habuit, totum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſtatim</hi> Clerum <hi>protectione ſua privavit;</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">Antiqu. Brit. in R. Winchelſey.</note> The King (ſaith the Hiſtorian) excluding the <hi>Clergy</hi> out of the Parliament, adviſed with his <hi>Barons,</hi> and his <hi>People</hi> only, what was beſt to be done; by whoſe Advice he put the <hi>Clergy</hi> out of his protection, and thereby forced them to conform to his Will and Pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>This is the <hi>Summa totalis</hi> of the Buſineſs, and comes unto no more but this, that a <hi>particular courſe</hi> was adviſed in Parliament on a <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Diſpleaſure</hi> taken by the King againſt the Body of his <hi>Clergy</hi> then convened together, for their particular refuſal to contribute to his Wants and Wars, the better to reduce them to their natural Duty. Which makes not any thing at all againſt the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the Houſe of <hi>Peers,</hi> or for <hi>excluding</hi> them that Houſe, or for the <hi>validity</hi> of ſuch Acts as are made in Parliament during the time of ſuch exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; eſpecially conſidering that the King ſhortly after called his <hi>States</hi> together, and did <hi>excuſe</hi> himſelf for many extravagant Acts which he had committed <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Wolſingh. in E.</hi> 1. <hi>An.</hi> 1297.</note> againſt the Liberties of the Subject, (whereof this was one) laying the blame thereof on his great occaſions, and the neceſſity which the Wars which he had abroad did impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
                  <p>And ſo much as in Anſwer unto that <hi>Record,</hi> ſuppoſing that the words thereof be rightly ſenced, as I think they are not, and that by <hi>Clerus</hi> there, we are to underſtand <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as I think we be not, there being no <hi>Record</hi> (I dare boldly ſay it) either of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory or Law, in which the word <hi>Clerus</hi> ſerves to ſignifie the <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> excluſive of the other <hi>Clergy,</hi> or any Writing whatſoever, wherein it doth either notſignifie the whole <hi>Clergy</hi> generally, or the <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Clergy</hi> only excluſive of the <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and other Prelates. Therefore in anſwer unto that ſo much applauded Cavil of <hi>Excluſo</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101709:8"/> 
                     <hi>Clero,</hi> from what Record ſoever it either hath been hitherto, or ſhall hereafter be produced, I ſhall propoſe it to the conſideration of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Reader, whether by <hi>Clerus</hi> in that place, or in any other of that kind and time, we muſt not underſtand the <hi>Inferior Clergy,</hi> as they ſtand diſtinguiſhed in the Laws from my Lords the Biſhops.</p>
                  <p>For howſoever it be true that <hi>Clerus</hi> in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Notion of the Word doth ſignifie the whole <hi>Clergy</hi> generally, Archbiſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prieſts and Deacons; yet in the Legal notion of it, it ſtands diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Prelates,</hi> and ſignifieth only the inferiour <hi>Clergy.</hi> Thus do we find the <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> of this Realm divided into <hi>Prelates, men of Religion,</hi> and other <hi>Clerks,</hi> 3 <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. the <hi>Seculars</hi> either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Clerks,</hi> 9 <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c,</hi> 3. or <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Clerks Beneficed,</hi> 18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. or generally into the <hi>Prelates</hi> and the <hi>Clergy,</hi> 9 <hi>E.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 15. 14 <hi>E. c.</hi> 1. &amp; 3. 18 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 2, 7. &amp; 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. 2, 4. &amp; 8 <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 1. And in all Acts and Grants of Subſidies made by the <hi>Clergy</hi> to the Kings or Queens of <hi>England</hi> ſince the 32<hi>d.</hi> of <hi>H.</hi> 8, (when the Clergy-Subſidies firſt began to be confirmed by Act of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>So alſo in the <hi>Latin</hi> Idiom, which comes neareſt home, <hi>Nos Praelati &amp; Clerus,</hi> in the ſubmiſſion of the <hi>Clergy</hi> to King <hi>H.</hi> 8. <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Regiſt. Watham.</hi>
                     </note> and in the Sentence of Divorce againſt <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Cleve</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">Regiſt. Cranmer.</note> and in the Inſtrument of the Grant of the Clergy-Subſidies preſented to the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ever ſince the 27th. of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> and in the form of the Certificates <hi>(per</hi> 
                     <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Stat.</hi> 8 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 17. <hi>&amp; ever ſince.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Praelatos &amp; Clerum)</hi> returned by every <hi>Biſhop</hi> to the Lord <hi>High Treaſurer,</hi> and finally, <hi>Nos Epiſcopi</hi> &amp; Clerus Cantuarienſis Provinciae <hi>in hac Synodo more noſtro ſolito, dum Regni Parliamentum</hi> celebratur, Congregati. <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Stat.</hi> 1. <hi>Phil. &amp; Mary, c.</hi> 8.</note> In the Petition to K. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> about the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the Abbey-Lands to the Patentees; ſo that though many Statutes have been made in theſe latter times, <hi>Excluſo Clero,</hi> the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, that is to ſay, the <hi>inferior Clergy</hi> (who anciently had their place in Parliaments) being quite ſhut out, and utterly excluded from thoſe publick Councils; yet this proves nothing to the Point, that any <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> hath been counted good, to which the Biſhops were not called, or at the making of which <hi>Act</hi> they either were <hi>ſhut out</hi> by Force, or excluded by Cunning.</p>
                  <p>But then, beſides the ſo much celebrated Argument of <hi>excluſo Clero,</hi> the Author of the Pamphlet before remembred, hath told us ſomewhat on the credit of <hi>Kilbancies</hi> book; In which the Juſtices are made to ſay 7 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>That our</hi> Sovereign Lord the King, <hi>may well hold his</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament <hi>by him, and his</hi> Temporal <hi>Lords, and by the</hi> Commons <hi>alſo, without the</hi> Spiritual <hi>Lords, for that the</hi> Spiritual Lords <hi>have not any place in the</hi> Parliament <hi>Chamber, by reaſon of their</hi> Spiritualities, <hi>but by reaſon of their</hi> Temporal <hi>Poſſeſſions. But firſt this is but the</hi> Opinion of a private man, of no Authority or Eſteem for ought we can can find) in the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore not concluding in ſo great a buſineſs. And <hi>2dly.</hi> admitting him to be a man of more note and credit than perhaps he was, yet he muſt needs fall ſhort in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, both for <hi>Abilities</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> of Chief Juſtice <hi>Coke,</hi> whoſe Judgment to the contrary we have ſeen before. But 3ly, it runs croſs to the ancient practice of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Times, in which the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſate in <hi>Parliament</hi> as <hi>Spiritual Perſons,</hi> without relation to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101709:8"/> their <hi>Temporal</hi> Poſſeſſions, or their <hi>Barons Fees,</hi> as afterwards in the Reign of the <hi>Norman</hi> Kings. And finally, admitting that <hi>Kilbancies</hi> Plea were of weight enough to keep the Biſhops down from riſing to their place in <hi>Parliament,</hi> it muſt be ſtrong enough to exclude all the <hi>Temporal</hi> Lords; The <hi>Temporal</hi> Lords being called to Parliament on no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ground, than for the <hi>Temporal</hi> poſſeſſions which they hold by Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rony. <hi>Adeo argumenta ab abſurdo petita, ineptos habent exitus,</hi> ſaid <hi>Lactantius</hi> truly, It is the Fate (ſaid he) of ill choſen <hi>Premiſes,</hi> that they produce ridiculous and abſurd <hi>Concluſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There remains one Objection more, and indeed the greateſt, not extant in the Pamphlet before remembred, though poſſibly promoted and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by it; that is to ſay, that the Biſhops are excluded from their Place and Vote by Act of Prrliament, deliberately made and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Kings conſent. For anſwer whereunto, it will be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firſt to ſtate this Queſtion, <hi>viz:</hi> Whether that any two of the <hi>the three Eſtates,</hi> concurring or agreeing together, may conclude any thing which tends to the Subverſion of the third. <hi>Bodinus</hi> that renwoned <hi>Stateſman,</hi> hath reſolved it negatively, and determined thus; <hi>Nihil a duobus ordinibus diſcerni poſſe, quo uni ex tribus incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum inferatur,</hi> &amp;c. <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bodin de Rep. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> That nothing can be done by two of the <hi>three Eſtates,</hi> to the diſprofit of the third, in caſe the point propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be ſuch as concerns them ſeverally; and he reſolved thus in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>Commons</hi> of the Realm of <hi>France,</hi> who were upon the point of being excluded from the Parliament, or Convention of the <hi>three Eſtates,</hi> if he had not notably beſtirred himſelf in their behalf (he being then a <hi>Delegate</hi> or Commiſſioner for one of the Provinces) and by his diligence and care preſerved their Intereſts; and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeve their Intereſt, he inſiſted cheifly on the antient cuſtom of the Realm of <hi>France,</hi> as alſo on the Realm of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Roman Empire;</hi> in each of which it was received for a ruled Caſe, <hi>Nihil a duobus ordinibus ſtatui poſſe, quo uni ex tribus prejudicium crearetur,</hi> That nothing could be done by any of the <hi>two Eſtates,</hi> unto the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the third.</p>
                  <p>And if it were a ruled Caſe; then in the Engliſh Parliaments, there is no reaſon why it ſhould be otherwiſe in the preſent times, the Equity and Juſtice of it being ſtill the ſame, and the ſame reaſons for it now as forcible as they could be then. Had it been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reſolved of in the former ages, wherein the <hi>Clergy</hi> were ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent in all publick Counſels, how eaſy a matter had it been for them, either by joyning with all the <hi>Nobility</hi> to exclude the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> or by joyning with the <hi>Commonalty</hi> to exclude the <hi>Nobles?</hi> Or having too much Conſcience to venture in ſo great a change, and alteration, ſo incompatible, Inconſiſtent with the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Parliament; how eaſily might they have ſuppreſſed the <hi>Potency,</hi> and impair the <hi>Priviledges</hi> of either of the other two, by by working on the humors or affections of the one to keep down the other?</p>
                  <p>Nor doth it help the matter in the leaſt degree to ſay that the Excluſion of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> from the Houſe of Peers, was not done meerly by the procurement of ſome of the other two Eſtates, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101709:9"/> by the Aſſent of the King, of whom the Laws ſay <hi>He can do no wrong,</hi> and by an Act of Parliament whereof our Lawyers ſay, <hi>que nul doit imaginer choſe diſhonourable,</hi> that no man is to think <note n="(†)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Plowden in Commen.</hi>
                     </note> diſhonourable. For we know well in what condition the King was when he paſſed that <hi>Act,</hi> to what extremities he was reduced, on what terms he ſtood, how he was forced to withdraw from his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London,</hi> to part with his dear Wife and Children, and in a word, ſo over-powred by the prevailing Party in the two Houſes of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that it was not ſafe for him (as his Caſe then was) to deny them any thing. And for the Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on, beſides that the Bill had been rejected when it was firſt brought unto the <hi>Lords,</hi> and that the greater part of the <hi>Lords</hi> were frighted out of the Houſe, when contrary unto the courſe of <hi>Parliament</hi> it was brought again; it is a point reſolved both in Law and Reaſon, that the Parliament can do nothing to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it ſelf, and that ſuch Acts as are under a conſtraint, are not good and valid, whereof we have a fair example in the book of Statutes. <note n="(†)" place="margin">15 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For whereas the King had granted certain Articles pretended to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Form of a Statute, expreſly contrary to the Laws of the Realm, and his own Prerogative and Rights Royal</hi> (mark it, for this is juſt the caſe) <hi>which he had yeilded to eſchew the dangers, which by denying of the ſame were like to follow in the ſame Parliament, it was</hi> repealed <hi>in theſe following</hi> words; <hi>It ſeemed good to the ſaid Earles, Barons, and other wiſe men, that ſince the Statute did not proceed of our Free</hi> Will, the ſame be void, and ought not to <hi>have the name nor ſtrength of a</hi> Statute, <hi>and therefore by their Counſel and Aſſent we have decreed the ſaid</hi> Statute <hi>to be void, &amp;c.</hi> Or if it ſhould not be repealed in a Formal Manner; yet is this Act however gotten, void in effect already by a former Statute, in which it was enacted in full Parliament, and at the ſelf ſame place where this Act was gained, That the <hi>Great Charter</hi> by which and many other Titles, the Biſhops held their place in Parliament) <hi>ſhould be kept in all points, and if any</hi> Statute <hi>be made to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it ſhall be held for none.</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 6. 1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>More Arguments than theſe againſt the Biſhops Place and Vote in Parliament I have no where found. And theſe being anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and refelled, I hope the point in queſtion hath been fairly proved, <hi>viz. That the Biſhops make a Fundamental and Eſſential part of our Engliſh Parliaments.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:101709:9"/>
                  <p>AN ANSWER TO THE GENTLEMAN'S <hi>Letter to his Friend:</hi> SHEWING THAT BISHOPS MAY BE JUDGES IN <hi>Cauſes Capital.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>PSAL. 82. 1.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deus ſtat in Congregatione Dei: in medio Deorum judicat.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Braddyll</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, 1680.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:101709:10"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101709:10"/>
                  <head>AN ANSWER TO THE <hi>GENTLEMAN</hi>'s <hi>Letter to his Firend:</hi> SHEWING THAT BISHOPS MAY BE JUDGES IN CAUSES CAPITAL.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Thank you for the Gentleman's Letter you ſent me, touching <hi>the Right of Biſhops ſitting as Judges in Caſes Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</hi> This <hi>Order</hi> of Men is not Sacred enough, it ſeems, in the Conſtitution, to ſecure it againſt (the Iniquity of theſe laſt Times) Attempts of Rage and Extirpation.</p>
                  <p>Not to mention <hi>Martin Mar-Prelates,</hi> nor others of former Times; within our own Memory, Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> led up the Van againſt them (1640.) in a Book of this Title, <hi>viz. [Lord-Biſhops, none of the Lords Biſhops.]</hi> After their <hi>Divine</hi> or <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical</hi> Conſtitution, they began to queſtion their <hi>Right</hi> to <hi>Sit</hi> in <hi>Parliament.</hi> This occaſioned that <hi>Quodlibetical</hi> Queſtion, <hi>[Whether the Biſhops make a Fundamental and Eſſential part of the</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101709:11"/> Engliſh <hi>Parliament.</hi> The Rational and Solid <hi>Anſwer</hi> to which Queſtion was Printed in 1661; and now Reprinted (as then put forth at firſt) <hi>for the Information of ſome, the Confirmation of others, and the ſatisfaction of all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Gentleman</hi> who wrote this Letter, ſeems to grant the Biſhops a large ſhare of Power within this Kingdom; yet as to <hi>Secular</hi> Matters, he does inſinuate ſome kind of <hi>Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> they are ſuppoſed to lie under, though his Arguments are very inconſequent to prove it. The <hi>Reſcript</hi> of <hi>Honorius</hi> (he ſaith) &amp; <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Decree</hi> of <hi>Juſtinian</hi> forbid them to have to do <hi>in Secular Matters?</hi> Therefore the Kings of <hi>England</hi> (who are of another Mind, upon good experience of their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and fidelity) may <hi>not admit</hi> them <hi>to have any Communion with Publick Functions:</hi> Nor is the Argument leſs inconſequent, which the <hi>Gentleman</hi> inſinuates from the Apoſtles Declaration and Practice. The Argument muſt be this, A few men are appointed by our Lord to propagate the Goſpel, and plant the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> all the world over; and they think it unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able they ſhould neglect this generous Employment (impos'd upon them immediately from Heaven, <hi>to ſerve Tables,</hi> that is, to relieve the Temporal Needs of indigent Diſciples) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Church is generally eſtabliſhed, Biſhops ſetled in every <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> and Miniſters in every <hi>Pariſh,</hi> it is equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable that the King ſhould intruſt any of the <hi>Clergy</hi> with any <hi>Secular Employments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But after theſe <hi>By-blows,</hi> this <hi>Gentleman</hi> tells us, <hi>This is none of his buſineſs</hi> (which he had therefore done better to have let alone;) 'Tis the <hi>Critical</hi> point he ſtands upon, which he calls <hi>Vexata Quaestio,</hi> what is to be done in Parliament, that is, in <hi>their Judicial way</hi> upon <hi>Trials,</hi> not in their <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Capacity, paſſing Acts of <hi>Attainder,</hi> in which the <hi>Gentleman</hi> is pleaſed to confeſs <hi>[I know that Biſhops have born a part; but</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that is not now the Queſtion, but only this, Whether the Lords Spiritual have a Right to ſtay and ſit in Court, till the Court proceeds to the Vote of Guilty, or Not Guilty.]</hi> This <hi>Gentleman</hi> concludes, They <hi>ought not.</hi> But the Queſtion truly and preciſely ſtated, is only this; Whether <hi>of Right</hi> they <hi>may</hi> or <hi>may not?</hi> And having di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently examined what hath been ſaid on both ſides (as the <hi>Gentleman</hi> hath adviſed me) I profeſs to differ from him, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſufficient Reaſon to change my Opinion, which is for the <hi>Affirmative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the better to carry on his <hi>Negative,</hi> this <hi>Gentleman</hi> falls upon <hi>Two Queſtions</hi> more, which may be thought <hi>preliminary</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101709:11"/> to this other. The Firſt is, touching the <hi>Peerage</hi> of the Lords Spiritual: The Second, Whether they make a <hi>Third Eſtate</hi> in Parliament? Theſe two fall in <hi>collaterally,</hi> and muſt be conſidered before we fall upon his main <hi>Battalia,</hi> muſtered up for the Defence of the Opinion we oppugn.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the Biſhops make a <hi>Third Eſtate</hi> in Parliament, there is very much alledged in the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> forementioned (from the Examples of all Chriſtian Kingdoms of the <hi>Gothick Model,</hi> from <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cooke,</hi> the Parliament-Rolls of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, and the <hi>Recognition</hi> of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal with the Commons, 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3. &amp; 8. and what is argued from thence, <hi>p.</hi> 16, 17. of <hi>the Rebels Plea,</hi> Printed 1660.) to which I ſhall add that Mr. <hi>Sheppard</hi> in his <hi>Grand Abridgment,</hi> and the Word <hi>Parliament</hi> tells us, That <hi>the Parliament in</hi> England <hi>is the Aſſembly of the King and the Three Eſtates of the Realm,</hi> viz. <hi>the Lords Spiritual, the Lords Temporal, and the Commons.</hi> And this <hi>Gentleman</hi> does acknowledge <hi>(p.</hi> 86) that <hi>the Subjects of</hi> England <hi>are divided into Three Eſtates, The Nobility the Clergy, and the Commonalty.</hi> Theſe, he ſaith, are the ſeveral <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the Kingdom. But if the Biſhops be not <hi>One</hi> of theſe <hi>Estates,</hi> then one of the <hi>Three Estates</hi> of the Kingdom is not <hi>Repreſented</hi> at all in Parliament (for he ſaith, <hi>(p.</hi> 88.) that <hi>the Convocation where all the Clergy are preſent in their</hi> Perſons, <hi>or their</hi> Repreſentatives, <hi>is no part of the Parliament,)</hi> which is abſurd. The Authority of Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ay, is moſt conſonant to Reaſon; and the Practice at the <hi>Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Peace</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King, 9 <hi>H.</hi> 5. &amp; 11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. are further Confirmations of it.</p>
                  <p>But this <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſaith <hi>(p.</hi> 88.) <hi>The Three Estates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are clean another thing; each muſt have a Negative Voice to all that paſſeth there:</hi> I might take notice by the By of his Miſtake herein; for there is nothing paſſeth where uſe is made of the <hi>Negative</hi> Voice: but <hi>I</hi> muſt obſerve, that this is a cleanly beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Queſtion. As for the Biſhops being <hi>intermingled</hi> with the <hi>Earls</hi> and <hi>Barons,</hi> and ſo if they be an <hi>Estate,</hi> it is an <hi>Eſtate</hi> within an <hi>Eſtate, like a Nest of Boxes, one within another,</hi> there is no abſurdity at all in it: for when <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd (not to recur to the time when all the Members of Parliament ſate in one Houſe together) the Piety and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thoſe times thought the <hi>State</hi> of the Church (with all its Rights and Intereſt) <hi>ſafe</hi> enough among the <hi>Nobility,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any peculiar <hi>Negative</hi> voice to ſecure it; and yet the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Proteſting</hi> (upon juſt occaſion) ſerves very well inſtead of ſuch a <hi>Negative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101709:12"/>
                  <p> But this <hi>Gentleman</hi> thinks it would be <hi>a great Diſparagement</hi> to the <hi>Peerage</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>Two Eſtates</hi> muſt be put together, to keep the <hi>Ballance even</hi> with the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> who are but <hi>One</hi> Eſtate; and that <hi>their Two ſhould ſignifie no more than that One:</hi> (taking no notice how much more they ſignifie, though they do very much,) To this I anſwer in the general, That <hi>Numbers</hi> of perſons add no <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Priviledge</hi> to <hi>a Politick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate:</hi> The <hi>Peerage</hi> of <hi>England</hi> had the ſame Power and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity when they were not half ſo Numerous.</p>
                  <p>But to be more particular, Experience tells us (and we have an Inſtance too freſh in memory) That neither the Biſhops <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> nor the Temporal Lords <hi>Negative Voice,</hi> nor the Kings <hi>Le Roy S'aviſera,</hi> are ſufficient to hold the Ballance even when the Commons depart from the Principles of Honour, Juſtice, and Loyalty. And as they never pretended to be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,</hi> ſo have they not always been obſerved to be ſo <hi>calm</hi> and <hi>ſteddy</hi> in their Proceedings, as becomes the Wiſdom and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of ſo Grave and Solemn a Convention. In 50 <hi>E.</hi> 3. they deſired, that the Lord <hi>Latimer,</hi> the King's <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> (for pretended Oppreſſion) might loſe <hi>all his Offices, and be no longer of the King's Council;</hi> which the King granted; yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards 51 <hi>E.</hi> 3. at the Requeſt of the <hi>Commons</hi> themſelves, <hi>he was reſtored to all, and declared innocent.</hi> This <hi>Gentleman</hi> was ſo ſenſible of this their <hi>Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Raſhneſs</hi> (attended with ſo much <hi>Levity)</hi> that he could not paſs it by, without ſetting ſome Remark upon it, <hi>p.</hi> 12.</p>
                  <p>But when <hi>Juſtice, Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> governs their Debates and Reſolutions, we may put the King, and (to uſe his own Illuſtration) all <hi>the Three Eſtates</hi> of Parliament into the ſame <hi>Nest of Boxes,</hi> and yet their reſpective <hi>Interests</hi> (which is the <hi>Interest</hi> of the whole Kingdom interwoven) will be <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,</hi> and preſerv'd inviolate.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Gentleman</hi> tells us further, That <hi>if the Biſhops be one of the Three Eſtates, nothing can paſs in</hi> Parliament <hi>without them.</hi> This may be generally true among States <hi>coordinate,</hi> without a <hi>Sovereign Head</hi> over them; and when a <hi>Rival</hi> is ſet up, to give <hi>Check-mate</hi> to the <hi>Sovereign</hi> Authority, as it was in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. mentioned by this Gentleman (at <hi>p.</hi> 92. when the Queſtion was <hi>[To whom the Supream Jurisdiction did belong, to the King, or to the Pope?]</hi> (In the time of ſuch a <hi>Competition,</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> is obliged to ſecure it ſelf againſt ſuch an <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> and does moſt juſtly abandon the <hi>Clergy</hi> that ſides with it.</p>
                  <p>But 2. If <hi>Acts</hi> have paſſed without the Biſhops, they have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101709:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> likewiſe done ſo (as by him is ſaid) ſometimes without the <hi>Commons. Egbert,</hi> who firſt united the Seven Kingdoms of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> under the common Name of <hi>England,</hi> he caus'd to be conven'd at <hi>London</hi> His <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Peers</hi> of the higheſt Rank, to adviſe upon ſome courſe againſt the <hi>Daniſh Pyrates,</hi> (this was a <hi>Military</hi> Buſineſs, and <hi>Bloud-ſhed</hi> might have enſued upon the Stubbornneſs of thoſe <hi>Pyrates)</hi> who infeſted the Sea-Coaſt of <hi>England.</hi> And King <hi>Ethelwolph</hi> in Parliament or Aſſembly of his States, at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> Anno 855. by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theſe Great Councils were the Parliaments of thoſe Times,</hi> Let. <hi>p.</hi> 72.</note> and Counſel of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Nobility,</hi> confirm'd unto the <hi>Clergy</hi> the <hi>Tenth Part</hi> of all mens Goods; and Ordered that the <hi>Tythe</hi> ſo confirmed unto them, ſhould be <hi>free</hi> from all <hi>Secular Services</hi> and <hi>Impoſitions.</hi> And <hi>Wingate</hi> in his <hi>Abridgment,</hi> and the Word <hi>Parliament,</hi> tells us, out of the <hi>Mirrour of Juſtices,</hi> of an Act in <hi>Aelfred's</hi> Time, <hi>That Parliaments ſhould be held twice a year, and oftner if need requir'd.</hi> But (note, ſaith he) <hi>This was by the King and Lords only.</hi> And I believe we may obſerve the like practice among ſome of this <hi>Gentleman's</hi> Precedents.</p>
                  <p>But it is much more ſatisfactory, when the Laws are Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Sovereign</hi> Authority, at the <hi>Request</hi> of the <hi>Commons,</hi> with the <hi>conſent</hi> of the Lords <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal;</hi> that is, by the <hi>King,</hi> with the joint <hi>Aſſent</hi> of the <hi>Three Eſtates</hi> of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; let us not therefore diſſolve or drive them away when we have them.</p>
                  <p>That which is alledged out of Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> and <hi>Crompton,</hi> I refer you to the <hi>Anſwer</hi> of the <hi>Quodlibetical</hi> Queſtion for your <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 93. to 98.</note> ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>That King <hi>James</hi> was of this Judgment, is evident from the very Words and Speech produced by this <hi>Gentleman</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. <hi>The Parliament</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is compoſed of a Head and a Body; The Head is the King, the Body are the Members of the Parliament: This Body again is ſubdivided into two parts; the Upper and the Lower Houſe; the Upper Houſe compounded partly of Nobility, Temporal men, who are Hereditable Counſellors to the</hi> High Court <hi>of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the Honour of their Creation and Lands; and partly of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Spiritual men, who are likewiſe by virtue of their Place and Dignity, Counſellors</hi> ad vitam, <hi>Life-Renters of this Court. The other Houſe is compos'd of Knights for the Shires, and Gentry and Burgeſſes for the Towns.]</hi> Here we ſee, though the King makes but <hi>Two Houſes,</hi> yet he does clearly diſtinguiſh them into <hi>Three Estates,</hi> though he does not call them ſo.</p>
                  <p>To what is ſaid by <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> and <hi>Finch,</hi> I oppoſe the Teſtimonies of <hi>Livy, Selden, Cooke</hi> and <hi>Sheppard:</hi> To the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101709:13"/> Expreſſions of the Late <hi>King</hi> of B. <hi>Memory,</hi> in his Anſwer to the 19 <hi>Propoſ.</hi> (when he was fluctuating in the midſt of a Storm ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering round about him,) and to the <hi>Declaration</hi> of the <hi>Commons,</hi> 2 <hi>H.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 32. I might Anſwer, That the <hi>Upper Houſe,</hi> in a <hi>large ſenſe</hi> (conſiſting of Lords Spiritual and Temporal ſitting and voting together) may be taken for <hi>One</hi> Eſtate: But taken <hi>preciſely,</hi> and in <hi>a ſtrict ſenſe,</hi> as their Concerns and Intereſts are diſtinct, ſo they are clearly <hi>Two.</hi> But to thoſe Authorities, I ſhall rather oppoſe the Act of <hi>Recognition,</hi> 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 3. Where the <hi>Lords</hi> Spiritual and Temporal, and the <hi>Commons</hi> in that Parliament Aſſembled, do <hi>Recognize</hi> the Queens Majeſty to be their true, lawful, and undoubted Sovereign Lieged Lady and Queen in theſe words, <hi>[We Your moſt Faithful, Loving, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Subjects, repreſenting the</hi> Three Eſtates <hi>of this Realm]</hi> which evidently ſheweth the <hi>Queen</hi> was not (there) eſteemed one. So when the Funerals of <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. were ended, the <hi>Three Eſtates</hi> did Aſſemble and Acknowledge his Son King. To think to elude ſuch Evidence, by ſaying (as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> does in the like caſe) that ſuch Expreſſions are delivered <hi>obiter,</hi> upon the By, is to make, what we fancy not, in any <hi>Statute,</hi> utterly <hi>void,</hi> and of none effect.</p>
                  <p>The next Queſtion concerns the Biſhops <hi>Peerage;</hi> For the <hi>Affirmative,</hi> we have theſe things to ſay,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the Prelates are called by the ſame <hi>Writ</hi> (for <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Manner)</hi> with that directed to the <hi>Temporal</hi> Barons: ſo the Anſwer to the <hi>Quodlibetical Queſtion:</hi> That they Sit and Vote there by a <hi>double capacity;</hi> as <hi>Biſhops</hi> firſt, in reference to their ſeveral <hi>Sees;</hi> and ſecondly, as <hi>Peers,</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</hi> Hereupon they affirm to the Lords <hi>Temporal</hi> in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden at <hi>Northampton Hen.</hi> 2. as <hi>Selden</hi> reports, <hi>We ſit not here as Biſhops only, but as Barons; we are Barons, and you are Barons; here we ſit as Peers.</hi> And ſome <hi>Statutes</hi> call them <hi>Peers</hi> of the Land <hi>in terminis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. 'Tis his <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi>'s Title, <hi>Primus Par Angliae.</hi> That the <hi>firſt Peer</hi> ſhould be no <hi>Peer,</hi> is an unheard of Sole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm. If he be a <hi>Peer,</hi> the reſt of the Biſhops are his <hi>Com-peers,</hi> what ever they are to the Lords <hi>Temporal. John Stratford</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of that place, in the time of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3, claim'd this Priviledge in the Right of his <hi>See.</hi> And the Proteſtat. of <hi>W. Courtney,</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where mentioned, with the reſt of the Biſhops, is another pregnant Evidence to this purpoſe. And 25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. The Prelates put up this Petition to the King (as the <hi>Gentleman</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf relates it, <hi>p.</hi> 83.) <hi>Seeing Archbiſhops and Biſhops hold their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralties</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101709:13"/> 
                     <hi>of the King</hi> in capite, <hi>and therefore are</hi> Peers <hi>of the Land as other Earls and Barons are, that you will be pleaſed to grant unto them, that no Judge may henceforward, for meer contempts, cauſe their</hi> Temporalties <hi>to be ſeized.</hi> Here we have a <hi>Prayer,</hi> that their <hi>Temporalties</hi> may not be <hi>ſeized,</hi> and the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of it; becauſe they are <hi>Peers,</hi> as <hi>Earls</hi> and <hi>Barons</hi> are. The King grants their <hi>Petition,</hi> and <hi>allows</hi> the Reaſon. The King cannot err in <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles;</hi> his <hi>Allowance</hi> therefore is a ſufficient <hi>confirmation</hi> of their <hi>Peerage.</hi> And this <hi>Gentleman, p.</hi> 93, &amp;c. when he argues againſt their being a <hi>third Eſtate,</hi> he tells us, <hi>William the firſt erected the temporalties of Biſhops into</hi> Baronies, <hi>to hold</hi> in capite; <hi>and upon account of thoſe</hi> Baronies, <hi>both the</hi> Temporal <hi>Lords and</hi> Spiritual <hi>had of right place in Parliament, and were bound to ſerve him there. They were all</hi> Foedal Barons, <hi>all holding by one tenure, and by that tenure ſitting in</hi> Parliament. And a little after he ſaith, <hi>They are ſtill qualifi'd to be Members of</hi> Parliament, <hi>as before, a Baron ſate as a Baron, an Earl as an Earl. Being made by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, or by Writ, or by holding ſuch a proportion of Land, alters not the Caſe as to their ſitting in</hi> Parliament; <hi>for it is being of ſuch a degree which makes them</hi> Peers <hi>of</hi> Parliament.] One would think this is cleer enough for the Biſhops <hi>Peerage.</hi> But beſides, either the Biſhops ſit in Parliament as <hi>Peers,</hi> or as <hi>Commoners:</hi> if as <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners,</hi> then his own Argument, <hi>p.</hi> 90. will be return'd upon him; <hi>Would it be for the Honour of the Houſe of Lord, that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners muſt be put to them, to keep the Ballance even with the Houſe of Commons? And moſt clearly it would be a Diſparagement to the Peerage of the Kingdom, the Temporal Lords, and would make them to be a poor Eſtate, that a number of Commoners muſt be joyn'd to them, to make up their</hi> Negative Voice, <hi>and ſet them upon even ground with the Houſe of</hi> Commons. But the truth is, the Biſhops Sit and Vote in Parliament (as we ſaid afore) by a <hi>double capacity;</hi> as <hi>Biſhops,</hi> firſt, in reference to their ſeveral <hi>Sees;</hi> and ſecondly, as <hi>Peers,</hi> in regard of their <hi>Baronies.</hi> All the Lords are <hi>equal</hi> in reſpect of their <hi>Peerage,</hi> and ſo they make up but <hi>one Houſe;</hi> but they are diſtinguiſh'd by their <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Spirituality</hi> reſpectively, and ſo they make up <hi>two Eſtates</hi> diſtinct and different.</p>
                  <p>But to prove that they are no <hi>Peers,</hi> this <hi>Gentleman</hi> fetches <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 85. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14, <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.</note> an Argument from <hi>Magna Charta</hi> it ſelf, I know it ſaith, <hi>Every man that is tried at the King's Suit, muſt be tried by his Peers,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be <hi>Amerced,</hi> or <hi>Impriſoned,</hi> or <hi>Diſſeiſed,</hi> or <hi>Outlaw'd,</hi> &amp;c. it muſt be <hi>by his Peers.</hi> But this Argument makes clear againſt him; for he himſelf informs us, <hi>p.</hi> 11, 12. that the Lord <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer,</hi> who was the King's <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> for Oppreſſion in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101709:14"/> places in <hi>Britain,</hi> and in <hi>England,</hi> was by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> adjudged to be <hi>impriſoned,</hi> and put to <hi>Fine</hi> and <hi>Ranſom;</hi> and the Lord <hi>John Nevil,</hi> a <hi>Privy Counſellor,</hi> for buying ſome Debts due by the King, at eaſie Rates, to make advantage to himſelf: He mentions ſome <hi>others,</hi> and concludes, <hi>At all theſe Trials the Biſhops were preſent, and no body ſayes but they might:</hi> which makes it evident (if the Law of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> were obſerved) that the Biſhops ſate as <hi>Peers</hi> in giving Judgment upon thoſe <hi>Culprit-Lords.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But for all this, the <hi>Gentleman</hi> hath a very ſtrong Objection out of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> againſt the Biſhops <hi>Peerage;</hi> and 'tis this, If any Biſhop be tried for any <hi>Capital</hi> Offence, he is tried by <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid.</hi> 85.</note> the <hi>Commoners,</hi> and that is the <hi>Common Law</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the Land; then (ſaith he) muſt <hi>Commoners</hi> be his <hi>Peers,</hi> and <hi>he</hi> and <hi>Commoners</hi> muſt be <hi>Pares.</hi> A <hi>Temporal Lord, Duke, Earl</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 86.</note> or <hi>Baron cannot be Judge in the caſe of a Biſhop, (out of Parliament) nor can any Biſhop be their Judge, how then can they be ſaid to be</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Fellow-Peers? <hi>For my part</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſee not.</hi> But I will undertake to read the Riddle to him: the King may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain</hi> his <hi>Favours,</hi> and <hi>limit</hi> his <hi>Grants</hi> as himſelf pleaſeth: the Dignities and Priviledges of the Lords Spiritual are not <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary</hi> like thoſe of the Lords Temporal, but only <hi>Perſonal,</hi> and conferr'd upon them in regard of their <hi>Holy Function.</hi> Hereupon, when they are <hi>impeached</hi> for any <hi>heinous Crime,</hi> which is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>deſecrate</hi> their perſons, they are <hi>interpretatively</hi> (though not <hi>formally) degraded</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Privilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um perſonale amittitur, extincta perſona cui id conceſſum eſt.</hi> And ſuch perſons are reputed dead in Law.</note>, and by a <hi>Fiction of Law</hi> (not <hi>unuſual) dead</hi> in that capacity, <hi>diveſted of their Peerage with their Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities,</hi> and ſo (being in the ſenſe of the Law reduced to that condition) they come to be tried as <hi>Commoners.</hi> And thus much for the Biſhops <hi>Peerage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. For their <hi>Right</hi> to Sit as Judges in <hi>Caſes Capital,</hi> as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>It deſerves a ſtrict enquiry, and we ſhould do well to conſider upon what ground the Prelates were prohibited having Votes in Caſes of Blood.</hi> Such a Prohibition indeed is extant; but it is Authentical only in the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> as we ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince anon: but this Law is <hi>Popiſh,</hi> grounded upon Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Superſtition, Uſurpation,</hi> and <hi>Papal Tyranny;</hi> and is very <hi>irrational</hi> and <hi>uncharitable,</hi> according to the uſual practice of it. This I doubt not to make appear to the unprejudiced and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader.</p>
                  <p>In the Interim, I think to remove a great miſtake of this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> who tells us, that <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> a <hi>Monk, one that would not be partial for the Lords Temporal in relating matters, to give them</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Let. p.</hi> 73.</note>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101709:14"/> 
                     <hi>more power in Judicature, and leſs to the Lords Spiritual, than of right belonged to each, and looking upon this excluſion of the Prelates from the power of Judging in ſuch caſes, to be ſome diminution of their Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency, which they were ſo ambitious of, he therefore ranks it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the</hi> Conſuetudines iniquas, <hi>the wicked Cuſtoms of the former times.</hi> I ſay, herein the <hi>Gentleman</hi> has committed a great <hi>miſtake.</hi> 'Tis true, their <hi>preſence</hi> in Parliaments, at ſuch <hi>Debates</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barr'd, and the reſtraint was put upon them by <hi>this</hi> Law, and none elſe: but ſo far were the <hi>Clergie</hi> of thoſe times from rank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Canon-Laws</hi> amongſt thoſe <hi>wicked Cuſtoms,</hi> that indeed they had it in too high a <hi>veneration;</hi> and <hi>this</hi> the <hi>Gentleman</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf obſerves in divers places of his Letters, averring it to be <hi>that Law, to which only the Clergy of thoſe times would be ſubject, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving themſelves above, and not bound by any other.</hi> p. 68. And ſome Laws before that, p. 22. He confeſſeth, <hi>The Canon Law was to them above all Laws, and what was forbidden by that Law, they could not have a thought that it could in any ſort be Lawful for them to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, as their right upon any account.</hi> This <hi>Gentleman</hi> knew, they did look upon it as <hi>ſacred:</hi> They <hi>appeal</hi> to it, and <hi>plead</hi> it for their <hi>exemption;</hi> and this he ſets down with his own Hand (at p. 20.) in theſe words: <hi>Quia in praeſenti Parliamento agitur de non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullis materiis in quibus non licet nobis alicui eorum juxta ſacrorum Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonum inſtituta, quomodo libet perſonaliter intereſſe:</hi> Becauſe in this preſent Parliament <hi>ſome things are to be tranſacted, at which it is not lawful for us, by the Decrees of the Holy Canons to be perſonally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent:</hi> This is the ground and reaſon of their proteſtation. The <hi>wicked Cuſtoms</hi> therefore which that <hi>Monk</hi> inveighs againſt, and which coſt <hi>Becket</hi> ſo ſevere a Penance, muſt be ſought for elſewhere, amongſt the <hi>reſt</hi> of thoſe <hi>Sixteen Conſtitutions</hi> of <hi>Clarendon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But whatever Opinion the <hi>Clergy</hi> of thoſe times had of this <hi>Canon,</hi> I doubt not to make it evident that it is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Principles of <hi>Superſtition,</hi> for as the Reverend <hi>Davenant</hi> hath <note place="margin">Determ. 11.</note> it, <hi>Quid impium, quid illicitum? What is in it that is impious, What that is unlawful, What that is contrary to the Office or Sacredneſs of a Prieſt where there is a juſt authority for it, to bridle and reſtrain ſuch as are notoriouſly wicked, and diſturbers of the Chriſtian Commonwealth, by civil penalties, and corporal inflictions? The Angels of Heaven think it no way diſagreeable, at Gods command, to inflict corporal puniſhments upon the wicked. And why ſhould the Angels of the Church at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the King, who is Gods Image upon Earth, think it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to adjudge the ſame wicked perſons to deſerve puniſhment? The Act and Exerciſe of civil Juriſdiction of its own nature is not diſagreeable</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101709:15"/> 
                     <hi>to the moſt holy perſon, nor any way oppoſite to the Sacerdotal Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. We have the Authority of God himſelf in the practice of his most Ancient Church, to justifie this Jurisdiction. Under the Law God himſelf joyn'd it to the Sacerdotal Office; it is not ſtrange there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, nor forbidden by Divine Law, that the Prieſt ſhould obtain a Civil Jurisdiction. We find it exemplified in</hi> Eli <hi>and</hi> Samuel, <hi>and</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Numb. 25. 7, 13.</note> 
                     <hi>the</hi> Maccabees, <hi>and all that were invested with the Office of</hi> High Prieſt. This could not be expected amongſt the <hi>Apostles,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then the <hi>Civil Magiſtrates</hi> were not <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> yet <hi>S. Peter</hi> had once a ſupply of <hi>Civil Authority</hi> by a <hi>Miracle;</hi> and to ſhew that it was not <hi>unlawful</hi> for an Apoſtle to give Sentence in <hi>Caſes Capital,</hi> He pronounc'd <hi>Saphira's</hi> Doom for <hi>Sacriledge</hi> and <hi>Lying,</hi> Acts 5. 9. <hi>Behold the feet of them which buried thy Husband, are at the Door, and ſhall carry thee out.</hi> But theſe <hi>New</hi> Maſters of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were afraid a <hi>Sentence</hi> of Juſtice ſhould defile them with the <hi>Blood</hi> of a Malefactor; like the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Elders</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews,</hi> John 18. 28. when they had bought and ſold the Life of our Bleſſed Lord, and uſed all the Tricks that Craft and Malice could ſuborn to deſtroy him; ſo <hi>preciſe</hi> they were for all that, they would not go into <hi>Pilates</hi> Judgment Hall, leaſt they ſhould be <hi>defiled</hi> and unfit <hi>to eat the Paſſover.</hi> 'Twas the <hi>Superſtition</hi> of thoſe Men, to think they could render the Prieſts <hi>Office</hi> more <hi>Sacred,</hi> and put more veneration upon his perſon, then Gods own Inſtitution had done. They would not have him intereſs or concern himſelf in <hi>a Caſe of Blood;</hi> leaſt it ſhould <hi>deſecrate</hi> and <hi>unhallow</hi> his Perſon, and <hi>ſtain</hi> his <hi>Function.</hi> But we know that all Virtue is <hi>Ornamental;</hi> and 'tis as well an <hi>Act of Justice,</hi> to condemn the <hi>Guilty,</hi> as to acquit the <hi>Innocent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Here is <hi>Uſurpation</hi> in this <hi>Canon,</hi> and it is flatly againſt the King's <hi>Supremacy.</hi> By this means a <hi>Foreign Power</hi> reſtrains the <hi>Sovereign Authority</hi> of the Kingdom from commanding the Service, or making uſe of the Duty of his Subjects in ſuch Caſes. The Force of this <hi>Canon</hi> divided the <hi>Prelates</hi> of thoſe times between the <hi>Prince</hi> and the <hi>Pope;</hi> either they did not underſtand, or they did wilfully neglect their Duty; and ſome Inſtances of the miſchievous effects hereof this <hi>Gentleman</hi> gives us in his Letter. He tells us, <hi>p.</hi> 7, 8. 5 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>The Parliament was declared to be called for the redreſs of the Breach of the Laws, and of the Peace of the Kingdom. And becauſe the</hi> Prelates <hi>were of opinion, that it belonged not properly to them to give counſel about keeping the Peace, nor puniſhing ſuch Evils, they went away by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and they returned no more.</hi> Nor did their Diſobedience
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101709:15"/> ſtop here; but the <hi>Gentleman</hi> tells us further, at <hi>p.</hi> 96. That 20 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <q>the Biſhops upon occaſion of the Statute of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, enter a Proteſtation againſt whatſoever ſhould be done in derogation or reſtriction of the Power of their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father the Pope, ſaying, they were ſworn to his Holineſs, and to the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </q> Theſe, and the like Inſolencies were the Fruits of thoſe <hi>Immunities</hi> which the <hi>Prelates</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> times received by the <hi>Decrees</hi> of thoſe <hi>Holy Canons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as <hi>this</hi> Canon was grounded upon <hi>Superſtition,</hi> and did <hi>confront</hi> the Kings <hi>Supremacy,</hi> ſo the Practice of it (in thoſe times) was <hi>irrational</hi> and <hi>uncharitable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt <hi>Irrational;</hi> for, 1. Why were the <hi>Prelates</hi> debarr'd the liberty of ſitting Judges in ſuch Caſes? Was it becauſe they wanted Knowledge, Reaſon, or Diſcretion? I ſuppoſe not: If it were not becauſe they had <hi>too little,</hi> but <hi>too much</hi> of theſe Qualifications: That was <hi>Irrational.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. That the <hi>Prelates</hi> have been, and may be Judges of <hi>Miſdemeanors,</hi> this <hi>Gentleman</hi> does grant, at <hi>p.</hi> 18. But there may be an <hi>Impeachment</hi> for ſundry <hi>Offences</hi> under the name of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> which really, according to the <hi>Rule</hi> of Law, are no more than <hi>Miſdemeanors.</hi> Why may not the Biſhops ſit as Judges <hi>in ſuch Caſes?</hi> Muſt the <hi>Culprit</hi> be delivered up to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> upon ſuch <hi>Impeachments,</hi> without any further <hi>Trial</hi> or <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,</hi> what will it amount unto? This would be a kind of <hi>Hallifax-Law;</hi> and that's <hi>Irrational.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the Caſe of Sir <hi>John Oldcaſtle,</hi> this <hi>Gentleman</hi> tells us, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 38, 39.</note> 
                     <q>The Popiſh Biſhops did excommunicate and condemn him for an Heretick, and ſo turn'd him over to the Secular Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>(for execution)</hi> yet certainly <hi>(ſaith this</hi> Gentlem. <hi>p.</hi> 39.) thoſe good men, I mean thoſe Popiſh Biſhops would have no more to do with him, as to his further Execution, that the World might ſee they were not men of Blood.</q> So that 'tis pretended at leaſt, that this <hi>Holy Canon</hi> (as they call it) was deſign'd for Caution, that the <hi>Prelates</hi> might have no <hi>hand in Blood;</hi> and yet the practice is ſo <hi>irrational,</hi> it does not ſufficiently prevent it. For in their <hi>Legiſlative capacity,</hi> this <hi>Gentleman</hi> grants, <hi>p.</hi> 3. that they may <hi>Sit,</hi> and <hi>Vote,</hi> and paſs <hi>Bills</hi> of <hi>Attainder</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>He ſaith p.</hi> 51 <hi>the E. of</hi> Straffords <hi>Trial was compleated that way.</hi>
                     </note>. And, <hi>p.</hi> 104. <q>Acts of Attainder are Laws, and every Freeman is ſuppoſed to give his conſent to every Law, either by his Repreſentative, or in perſon, if a Member of Parliament; and Biſhops being Members, may, I think <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> claim to do it perſonally.</q> And though there be a great ſtir about ſuch things as are <hi>preliminary,</hi> and <hi>preparatory to</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101709:16"/> 
                     <hi>Condemnation,</hi> yet the <hi>Constitutions</hi> of <hi>Clarendon</hi> enjoyned them <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Let. p.</hi> 71.</note> to attend the Court <hi>quouſque perveniatur ad diminutionem Membro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, vel ad Mortem;</hi> till it comes <hi>to loſs of Life or Member</hi> (which the <hi>Lawyers</hi> underſtand to be the Sentence of <hi>Guilty</hi> or <hi>Not Guilty.)</hi> Now I would fain be reſolved, whether <hi>theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings</hi> be not <hi>in agitatione cauſae ſanguims?</hi> whether accoording <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 1.</note> to this practice a <hi>Caſe of Blood</hi> be not all the while in <hi>agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> And then reflecting upon the <hi>Gentlemans</hi> Rule in <hi>Logick, Cauſa cauſae eſt cauſa cauſati,</hi> and upon the Story of <hi>Chaucer</hi>'s Frier, let the Reader pleaſe to peruſe <hi>p.</hi> 64, 65, 66, of the <hi>Letter,</hi> and then judge whether the practice be not, (as I ſaid) <hi>Irrational.</hi> And then,</p>
                  <p>Secondly, This practice of thoſe <hi>Popiſh</hi> times was <hi>uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable;</hi> for if the Biſhops were debarr'd ſitting as Judges in ſuch <hi>Caſes Capital,</hi> out of a <hi>ſuspition</hi> of their <hi>Integrity,</hi> it was <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable</hi> to the Biſhops; if out of a jealouſie they might be too <hi>ſoft</hi> and <hi>yielding</hi> in their clemency, it were <hi>uncharitable</hi> to the <hi>Delinquent;</hi> if out of <hi>fear</hi> they might be too <hi>ſevere</hi> in point of Juſtice, it is <hi>uncharitable</hi> to the <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> for Diſcretion ought to take her Rules from Charity, when <hi>Pity,</hi> and when <hi>Severity</hi> are to be uſed for the advantage of the Publick. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Justice</hi> may be provoked into <hi>Severity,</hi> and when <hi>Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are preferr'd with <hi>rigour,</hi> 'tis poſſible the <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> of ſuch grave and holy perſons intervening, a <hi>raſh</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſable</hi> Sentence may be ſtopt and prevent a Deluge of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, which might otherwiſe enſue. <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>See the Caſe,</hi> p. 26, 27, 28. <hi>of the Letter.</hi>
                     </note> Had the Biſhops been preſent at <hi>Haxeye</hi>'s Trial, they might as well have prevented his Condemnation, as obtained his Pardon.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Canon-Law</hi> then gave the firſt <hi>riſe</hi> and <hi>beginning</hi> to this Uſage (as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſeems to acknowledge, <hi>p.</hi> 68.) But the Ground of that <hi>Canon</hi> was <hi>Superstition,</hi> and it did <hi>confront</hi> the Kings <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and was <hi>irrational</hi> and <hi>uncharitable</hi> in the practice of it: Let us therefore examine what <hi>Force</hi> it had, and by what <hi>Authority.</hi> That this was in uſe while the <hi>Pope</hi> had a <hi>concurrent Jurisdiction</hi> here, cannot be denied; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever it received a <hi>Civil Sanction,</hi> and an <hi>expreſs Ratification,</hi> and had <hi>the ſtamp of Parliament-Authority ſet upon it,</hi> is the matter now in queſtion. And this I do ſtedfaſtly deny, and the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi> as earneſtly affirm and contend for.</p>
                  <p>To prove this, he does alledge a <hi>double confirmation,</hi> and to give it the more <hi>Credit,</hi> he carries it up as high as the dayes of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor. But I deſire the Reader to obſerve, that in the management of his Evidence, he turns an <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101709:16"/> into a <hi>Prohibition;</hi> a <hi>Priviledge</hi> into a <hi>compleat Act</hi> of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and a <hi>Proteſtation</hi> into a <hi>Statute.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He does alledge the <hi>Year-Book</hi> of 10 <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>Term. Paſch. n.</hi> 35. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Let. p.</hi> 78.</note> Where we have ſet down the manner of their <hi>Trials</hi> in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <q>[When a Lord is indicted, &amp;c. he ſhall plead <hi>Not Guilty,</hi> and this ſhall be tried by his Peers; and then the Lords Spiritual, <hi>who may not conſent to the Death of any man,</hi> ſhall make their <hi>Proctor,</hi> &amp;c. This <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> I alledge, to ſhew that even by the Law of the Land, the Biſhops cannot be Judges in a Caſe Capital.]</q> Here the <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſays, <hi>Their making a</hi> Proctor, <hi>was</hi> Error Temporis; <hi>the Error of thoſe Times.</hi> Why? Becauſe that practiſe was not for his purpoſe. But, if, by the <hi>Law of the Land,</hi> he means the <hi>Statute-Law</hi> (as he ſeems to do) I muſt have a <hi>Writ of Error,</hi> to <hi>reverſe</hi> his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For the <hi>Pope</hi> having then a <hi>concurrent Jurisdiction</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Canon-Law</hi> was in <hi>force</hi> amongſt them; and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that <hi>the Lords Spiritual might not conſent to the Death of any man,</hi> they have reſpect to the <hi>Prohibition</hi> of the <hi>Canon-Law,</hi> but this is not any the <hi>leaſt confirmation</hi> of it.</p>
                  <p>But this <hi>Gentleman</hi> will needs have it confirmed by a <hi>Civil Sanction,</hi> and ſo become the Law of the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>firſt Confirmation,</hi> he ſaith, was about the time of 10 <hi>H.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 69, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 2. amongſt the <hi>ſixteen Conſtitutions of</hi> Clarendon, <hi>which</hi> (beſides the Authority of Parliament (to make the Obſervation of them the more inviolable) <q>were eſtabliſhed by the Solemnity <note place="margin">
                           <hi>p.</hi> 72.</note> of an Oath, which is the greateſt Obligation that Mankind is capable of, making even God a Party to it, to ſee it obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and puniſh the Tranſgreſſors.</q> Here is a fair <hi>Plea</hi> for a ſolemn <hi>Confirmation,</hi> if the <hi>Gentleman</hi> were not <hi>partial</hi> or <hi>miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> in the Buſineſs. But the Caſe was this, upon the account of their <hi>Immunities,</hi> the <hi>Prelates</hi> eſpecially grew very <hi>remiſs</hi> and <hi>careleſs</hi> of their Duties (as was noted formerly.) Hereupon, in that <hi>Great Council (which was then their Parliament) amongſt the reſt,</hi> the King made this, (the 11th. of thoſe Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,) <q>The Archbiſhops, Biſhops, <hi>&amp; univerſae perſonae Regni,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>p.</hi> 71.</note>
                     </q> (not all the <hi>Dignified Clergy</hi> of the Land, as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it, but) <q>all perſons whatſoever, who have a Tenure <hi>in capite,</hi> ſhall hold their poſſeſſions from the King as a <hi>Barony,</hi> and ſhall anſwer for their Eſtates unto the Kings Juſtices and Miniſters, and ſhall obſerve and obey all the Kings Laws; and together with other Barons they are to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in all Judgments in the Kings Courts.</q> [This is the <hi>Duty</hi> they are obliged and ſolemnly ſworn to; and then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101709:17"/> an <hi>Indulgence</hi> or <hi>Priviledge]</hi> till the Sentence comes <hi>to the loſs of Life or Member;</hi> and here they are left to their <hi>Liberty</hi> to obſerve the <hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>Holy Canon.</hi> Hereupon <hi>we may</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 73.</note> 
                     <hi>build our Faith, that there was</hi> really <hi>ſuch an Uſage</hi> (as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> infers) <hi>in ancient times, and that a liberty</hi> was left to continue it (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Canon,</hi> and in veneration of it) but that 'twas <hi>ratified</hi> and <hi>confirmed,</hi> we have not one Syllable to prove it.</p>
                  <p>The Second <hi>Confirmation</hi> this <hi>Gentleman</hi> finds, was in 11 <hi>R.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 71, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> 2. upon the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of the <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> for himſelf and the other Biſhops. And here (after ſome <hi>fluctuation</hi> and <hi>unſteadi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,) p.</hi> 75. to make it a <hi>Law,</hi> he tells us, <q>The ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enacted did conſiſt of two Particulars; the one, That the Prelates had a Right to ſit and vote in all other Buſineſſes;</q> 
                     <hi>the other,</hi> 
                     <q>That they had no Right, nor was it lawful for them to be preſent in Parliament, when ſuch Buſineſſes were in queſtion:</q> 
                     <hi>But the</hi> Tenour <hi>of their Proteſtation is,</hi> 
                     <q>That they intend to be preſent, to conſult, to treat of, and to determine, <hi>in omnibus,</hi> in all things, ſaving their Rights, their State and Dignity. <hi>But becauſe</hi> ſome things were to be tranſacted in that Parliament, at which, by the Decrees of the Sacred Canons, it was not lawful for them to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally preſent, therefore they proteſted, that while ſuch things were in agitation, they would abſent themſelves. Which Proteſtation, being read in Full Parliament, at the inſtance and prayer of the Archbiſhop and other Prelates, was entred upon the Parliament-Roll, by the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, with the Aſſent of the Lords Temporal and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</q> This, the <hi>Gentleman</hi> will needs contend to be a <hi>Law</hi> of Parliament, (or a <hi>Law of the Land.)</hi> Why? Becauſe it was <hi>entred in the Roll or Journal-Book,</hi> that ſuch a thing was <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon by the King and Two Houſes;</hi> 
                     <q>Which (ſaith he) was all the Formality of paſſing Laws in Parliament, in <note place="margin">
                           <hi>p.</hi> 23.</note> thoſe times.</q> But what was it that the Biſhops petitioned might be <hi>entred</hi> upon the <hi>Parliament-Roll?</hi> Was it the <hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>Sacred Canons,</hi> which debarr'd their preſence in the <hi>Houſe</hi> at ſuch Debates? <hi>That</hi> indeed had been ſomewhat to the purpoſe: but here was no ſuch matter deſired; it was their <hi>Proteſtation:</hi> and if every thing that is <hi>entred</hi> upon the <hi>Parliament-Roll</hi> by the <hi>Agreement</hi> of the King and the Two Houſes, becomes <hi>an Act of Parliament</hi> forthwith, then let this <hi>Protestation,</hi> for the <hi>preſent,</hi> paſs for an <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament; and we ſhall ſee anon what it will amount to.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101709:17"/>
                  <p> In the Interim let us return to the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> where there ſeems to be moſt colour for ſuch a Confirmation. There we may obſerve <hi>Two</hi> things in that 11th. <hi>Conſtitution, a Duty enjoyned,</hi> the Prelates <hi>attendance at the Kings Courts;</hi> and then a <hi>Liberty</hi> or <hi>Priviledge</hi> indulged; <hi>That they may withdraw and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear that attendance, when it comes to ſentence for loſs of Life or Member.</hi> That <hi>this</hi> is a <hi>Priviledge</hi> or a <hi>Liberty,</hi> cannot be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> reckons it <hi>inter Libertates,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Ancient Liberties</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Let. p.</hi> 71.</note>; and this <hi>Gentleman</hi> could not chuſe but obſerve it, (though it was not for his purpoſe to diſtinguiſh this <hi>Priviledge</hi> from the <hi>Injunction)</hi> 
                     <q>One would think (ſaith he) they <hi>(the Biſhops)</hi> might look upon <hi>(it)</hi> as a Right and Priviledge, to be exempt from being obliged to attend in ſuch Caſes, Caſes of Blood.</q> If a <hi>Priviledge,</hi> then I may <hi>uſe</hi> or I may <hi>forbear</hi> it. To ſay, I <hi>may</hi> do ſuch a thing, therefore I <hi>ſhall</hi> do it, is <hi>irrational;</hi> ill <hi>Logick,</hi> and worſe <hi>Polity. Priviledges,</hi> ſay the <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers,</hi> are <hi>Franchiſes</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> or <hi>Immunities</hi> granted to a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> an <hi>Office,</hi> or a <hi>Corporation.</hi> Such as have them, may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>enjoy</hi> or <hi>refuſe</hi> them. It is the <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>Attorneys</hi> and <hi>Clerks</hi> in they <hi>Kings</hi> Bench, they cannot <hi>be preſt for Soldiers,</hi> they cannot be <hi>compell'd to bear Offices in their Pariſhes;</hi> yet <hi>Volunteers</hi> they may be in both Caſes. No man ſhould be <hi>compell'd</hi> to uſe his <hi>Priviledge;</hi> for then his <hi>Franchiſe</hi> would be no <hi>Liberty,</hi> but the more <hi>inthrall</hi> him. We may obſerve accordingly, that the <hi>Prelates</hi> very well underſtood this their <hi>Liberty;</hi> for ſometimes they would <hi>uſe</hi> their Priviledge, <hi>abſent</hi> themſelves, when <hi>Caſes Capital</hi> were upon <hi>Trial,</hi> and <hi>withdraw,</hi> when Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Blood</hi> were in agitation; and this is obvious to every eye in the peruſal of the <hi>Gentlemans</hi> Letters. But many times (which is very conſiderable in the Caſe) when they did <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw,</hi> they either made a <hi>Proxy</hi> to repreſent them, or entered their <hi>Proteſtation</hi> to preſerve their <hi>Rights.</hi> 'Tis true, the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi> does except againſt their way of <hi>Proxy's,</hi> as <hi>Unparlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary;</hi> and <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four</hi> Exceptions he hath, which are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to <hi>elude</hi> any Teſtimony: For either it is <hi>Error Temporis,</hi> an Errour of thoſe times; or ſpoken <hi>obiter,</hi> upon the By, and of no importance; or it is <hi>unparliamentary</hi> and extravagant, or elſe <hi>Repealed:</hi> Such a proviſion of <hi>Evaſions</hi> as may ſerve to help a man out of the <hi>Nooſe</hi> of any Argument that can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in Matters of this Nature.</p>
                  <p>For the <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> he would <hi>elude</hi> the <hi>force</hi> of that, by ſaying, <q>Their <hi>Salvo,</hi> that which they would enſure to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <note place="margin">
                           <hi>p.</hi> 21.</note> is their Right of ſitting to conſult, treat of, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101709:18"/> in that, and all other Parliaments, when Capital Caſes are not in queſtion:</q> but there was no need of a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation</hi> to this effect: This was their <hi>Duty,</hi> to which the <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendon Conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>a Solemn Oath</hi> obliged them. When men proteſt a <hi>Right,</hi> 'tis not to be underſtood of <hi>that</hi> Right which no man doubts of, and therefore is not liable to queſtion; but of <hi>that Right</hi> which they give ſome <hi>colour</hi> to be <hi>queſtion'd,</hi> becauſe they <hi>decline</hi> and <hi>forbear</hi> the <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of it: <hi>This</hi> was a <hi>Right</hi> to <hi>debate, vote</hi> and <hi>ſit</hi> as <hi>Judges</hi> in <hi>Caſes Capital,</hi> if poſſibly the <hi>Decree</hi> of that <hi>Canon</hi> ſhould come to be <hi>null</hi> (as now it is) or <hi>altered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I muſt not forget to tell you of <hi>two Rules</hi> obſervable about ſuch <hi>Priviledges</hi> as are granted to Subjects by the King, as this of the <hi>Clarendon Conſtitution</hi> was to the <hi>Prelates.</hi> The firſt is, That <hi>they are not to be underſtood to debar the Kings Commands,</hi> nor ought to be a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> to his <hi>Sovereign Authority,</hi> for this were a <hi>derogation</hi> to his <hi>Royal Office,</hi> a diminution to his <hi>Crown and Dignity;</hi> not to be granted by him upon any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. By the Conſtitutions of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> the King did <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt</hi> the Biſhops from <hi>attending</hi> his Court of Parliament at <hi>ſuch Trials</hi> in <hi>Capital Caſes</hi> in general; but he did not <hi>abſolve</hi> them from their <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> to his own <hi>special commands,</hi> upon any juſt occaſion. Hereupon in the 11th. <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. Archbiſhop <hi>Becket,</hi> in a <hi>Solemn</hi> Council at <hi>Northampton,</hi> being accuſed of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and other Miſdemeanors, where <hi>Biſhops</hi> were his <hi>Judges,</hi> as well as <hi>Temporal</hi> Lords; when thoſe <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops could not agree about pronouncing the Judgment, they putting it off from one to the other;</hi> at laſt <hi>the King commanded</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> to <hi>do it.</hi> This hapned <hi>ſoon after</hi> the <hi>Ratification</hi> of the <hi>Clarendon Conſtitutions,</hi> which all the Lords and Biſhops had taken their <hi>corporal Oath</hi> to obſerve for ever: And it is not to be imagined they could forget what had been ſo <hi>lately</hi> done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them; wherefore we muſt conclude that <hi>they</hi> did not take themſelves to be obliged either by that <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> to <hi>abſent</hi> themſelves <hi>alwayes</hi> from <hi>ſuch</hi> Trials; for though the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> ſaith, <hi>Debent intereſſe judiciis curiae Regis, ſicut caeteri Barones;</hi> 
                     <q>That they ought, as well as other Barons, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend all the Judgments of the Kings Court; <hi>quouſque perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niatur ad diminutionem membrorum, vel ad mortem;</hi> till the Matter comes to Sentence, for the loſs of Life or Member.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet (whatſoever <hi>William</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the reſt of the Biſhops had ſaid in their <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> 11 <hi>R.</hi> 2.) The <hi>Constitution</hi> of <hi>Clarendon</hi> doth not ſay, <hi>Debent ſe abſentare,</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101709:18"/> that the Biſhops <hi>ought to withdraw and abſent themſelves</hi> from ſuch Sentence. This <hi>Gentleman</hi> endeavours to <hi>invalidate</hi> this ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 60, 61.</note> an Evidence, becauſe it is taken out of a <hi>Manuſcript</hi> made by the Monk <hi>Stephanides;</hi> and none of the <hi>Ancient Hiſtorians</hi> of thoſe times ſay any thing of <hi>Becket</hi>'s being <hi>accuſed for Treaſon.</hi> But I muſt tell you, 'tis not the <hi>Print</hi> that adds <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to any Writing; and I ſhall truſt Mr. <hi>Selden</hi>'s Judgment, rather than this <hi>Gentlemans</hi> Conjectures: Beſides, <hi>A Negative Argument from Authority</hi> is of no force; for why do we read va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of <hi>Historians</hi> upon the ſame Subject; but becauſe we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what one fails in for want of Memory or Information, another may ſupply by a better Diligence and Enquiry.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Second Rule</hi> obſervable in matters of <hi>Priviledge,</hi> is this, <hi>Privilegia omnia ſine prejudicio Tertii concedenda &amp; conceſſa intelligenda ſunt;</hi> 
                     <q>We muſt underſtand all priviledges that are granted, to be granted without any prejudice to any third perſon.</q> Now this <hi>Gentleman</hi> quotes <hi>Brompton</hi>'s Chronicle, reciting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 108.</note> the Laws of King <hi>Athelstan,</hi> this concerning Biſhops; <hi>Debent Epiſcopi cum ſeculi Judicibus intereſſe Judiciis, ne permittant, ſi poſſint, ut aliqua pravitatum germina pullulaverint;</hi> 
                     <q>The Biſhops ought to be preſent in Judgments with the Secular Judges, not to ſuffer any Buds of wickedneſs to ſprout up if they can hinder it.</q> And does not the Law of God oblige ſuch as are in Authority, to uſe their Power as well to <hi>reſcue</hi> the oppreſſed, as to <hi>puniſh</hi> evil doers? Let us conſult the wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 11, 12. <hi>If thou forbear to deliver them that are drawn unto death, and thoſe that are ready to be ſlain; if thou ſaiſt, Behold we knew it not; doth not he that pondereth the Heart conſider it? and he that keepeth thy Soul, doth not he know it? and ſhall not he render to every man accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his works?</hi> This, ſaith the Author of the <hi>Synopſis,</hi> concerns eſpecially ſuch as are in <hi>Authority:</hi> And (as Dr. <hi>Tho. Cartwright</hi> comments upon the place) <hi>Quamvis periculum certum non ſit, ſi tamen ſuſpitio aliqua mortis imminentis justa ſubſit, non eſt cunctandum, donec morti quis adjudicatus fuerit; facilior enim eſt Liberatio, dum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itus adhuc dubius eſt, quam cum lata eſt Mortis ſententia:</hi> And I muſt not omit what the ſame Author ſaith a little after; <hi>Quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum autem inſontes, ſi poſſis, non liberare; ſic maleficorum, quantum in te eſt ſupplicium non promovere, atrox flagitium eſt:</hi> and for this, the ſaid <hi>Cartwright</hi> quotes the ſame <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 17. 15. This is a matter of ſo great importance, every man who has a <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of Judicature, ought eſpecially to conſider it. And if this <hi>Gentleman</hi> be as ſincere in his Profeſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Biſhops (which I have no reaſon to queſtion) as he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101709:19"/> is juſt and modeſt in ſaying, that <hi>he does not envy them their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> I hope he will be ſo ingenuous alſo, as not to <hi>deny</hi> the <hi>King</hi> their <hi>faithful counſel,</hi> nor the Countrey their <hi>pious Aid</hi> and <hi>Service.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the Body of his Epiſtle, it conſiſts of <hi>Record</hi> and <hi>Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> which moſt men want means and <hi>opportunity</hi> to examine <note n="*" place="margin">This Task therefore is faln into a more able hand.</note>, and very many <hi>skill</hi> to conſtrue and comment on: This is the Evidence which this <hi>Gentleman</hi> does produce, and that it may be the better underſtood, I ſhall lay down ſome undoubted <hi>Principles, Rules</hi> and <hi>Obſervations,</hi> that the Reader may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter judge of it. And I ſhall obſerve,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Lords <hi>Spiritual,</hi> being <hi>Barons, Peers,</hi> and <hi>Great men,</hi> they are many times comprehended under <hi>theſe Titles,</hi> when they are not ſtiled by their <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>diſtinctive</hi> Names of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> or <hi>Prelates.</hi> I ſhall need to inſtance in no more than that of <hi>Magnates,</hi> Great men. In the Reign of <hi>Edrid</hi> (948) we read thus, <hi>In Feſto Nativitatis B. Mariae, cum univerſi Magnates</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Here Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops and Biſhops are</hi> Magnates <hi>as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Regni per Regium edictum ſummoniti, tam Archiepiſcopi, &amp; Epiſcopi, quam caeteri totius Regni Proceres, &amp; Optimates</hi> Londini, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>A Negative Argument from Authority is of no validity,</hi> v. g. Such a Writer does not report ſuch a thing; therefore there was no ſuch Matter: this does not follow.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>The practice</hi> of <hi>Ancient</hi> times, in the <hi>caſe</hi> before us, was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>variable:</hi> For they were under the <hi>Popes</hi> Juriſdiction, <hi>who</hi> kept the <hi>Canon-Law</hi> in force; and among the reſt, this <hi>Canon</hi> touching the Biſhops <hi>Receſs</hi> from all <hi>Trials</hi> in <hi>Caſes capital.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In obedience to which <hi>Canon</hi> they did, for the moſt part, <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> themſelves. But when <hi>H.</hi> 2. by the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendon</hi> enjoyned all <hi>Prelates,</hi> as well as other <hi>Barons,</hi> to attend his Courts, he granted them withal a <hi>Liberty</hi> or <hi>Priviledge</hi> to <hi>abſent</hi> themſelves (if they ſhould think good) from <hi>Trials</hi> of <hi>that</hi> nature: Hereupon <hi>they</hi> did <hi>ſometimes</hi> uſe their Priviledge, and <hi>abſented</hi> themſelves; <hi>ſometimes</hi> they did <hi>refuſe</hi> their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and <hi>ſate</hi> as Judges.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. We may obſerve how the Matter was carried, running through all the <hi>Trials</hi> upon <hi>Record,</hi> as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> gives ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them <note n="†" place="margin">With what care and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity is left to others to examine and make report.</note>, and in <hi>his</hi> Method.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt is 4 <hi>E.</hi> 3. in <hi>Mortimers</hi> Caſe; where we have <hi>Earls, Barons,</hi> the <hi>Peers;</hi> afterwards, <hi>Earls, Barons</hi> and <hi>Peers:</hi> the Biſhops may be comprehended under either Title of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> or <hi>Peers;</hi> for they were both.</p>
                  <p>5 <hi>E.</hi> 3. The Biſhops <hi>would</hi> not underſtand their <hi>Duty</hi> at all: they would neither <hi>keep the peace,</hi> nor <hi>puniſh</hi> a <hi>Battery.</hi> This was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101709:19"/> 
                     <hi>a ſtupid Neglect;</hi> but ſignifies nothing to the deciding of the Controverſie.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. The Biſhops may be comprehended under the Name of <hi>Grantz, Magnates,</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> men.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. 42 <hi>E.</hi> 3. Here the Biſhops were preſent by their title of <hi>Prelates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. 50 <hi>E.</hi> 3. The Biſhops were <hi>preſent</hi> at theſe <hi>Trials,</hi> yet <hi>two</hi> of the De linquents were <hi>Lords.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. They <hi>were,</hi> and they <hi>were not</hi> preſent; the Caſe is <hi>doubtful.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. 3 <hi>R.</hi> 2. If the Biſhops were <hi>not</hi> preſent, 'tis confeſt they <hi>might</hi> have been; for what was done, was done by the <hi>Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Power,</hi> and in <hi>that capacity</hi> to paſs <hi>Bills</hi> of <hi>Attainder,</hi> the <hi>Gentleman</hi> grants they have a <hi>Right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. 4 <hi>R.</hi> 2. If the Biſhops be <hi>Peers</hi> of the <hi>Realm,</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> of Parliament, they might be comprehended there. To ſay they are always expreſt by the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Prelates,</hi> is to <hi>beg</hi> the Queſtion.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. 7 <hi>R.</hi> 3. It ſeems the Lords <hi>Spiritual</hi> were <hi>abſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. 10 R. 2. Here the Biſhops were <hi>preſent,</hi> and <hi>judged</hi> of <hi>Miſdemeanors,</hi> which (for ought we know) upon <hi>Trial,</hi> might have amounted to <hi>Merit</hi> of Death.</p>
                  <p n="11">11, 11 R. 2. The Biſhops were <hi>virtually</hi> preſent by their <hi>Proteſtation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. 20 R. 2. <hi>Thomas Haxey</hi> Clerk (whether he was a Member of the Houſe may be a queſtion) but his fault (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever aggravated) ſeems to be but a <hi>Miſdemeanor,</hi> at the <hi>Trial</hi> whereof, the Biſhops had <hi>right</hi> undoubtedly to be preſent; whether they were preſent, ſeems <hi>doubtful:</hi> but 'tis moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it had been more <hi>ſafe</hi> and <hi>charitable</hi> to prevent the Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, than to run the hazard of an <hi>After-Game,</hi> when he was condemn'd, to ſeek his Pardon.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. 21 R. 2. In this Parliament, the Biſhops were preſent by their <hi>Repreſentative,</hi> by <hi>Proxy,</hi> and that <hi>three</hi> ſeveral times, upon <hi>three</hi> ſeveral Occaſions.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. Here they were <hi>preſent,</hi> but gave no Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. 2 <hi>H.</hi> 4. It does not <hi>appear</hi> that the Biſhops were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. 5 <hi>H.</hi> 4. The Biſhops may be comprehended under the title of <hi>Peers,</hi> and the Matter being found but a <hi>Treſpaſs,</hi> their <hi>right</hi> of Sitting, the <hi>Gentleman</hi> cannot deny them.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101709:20"/> 17. 7 <hi>H.</hi> 4. Here the King <hi>commanded</hi> the Advice <hi>only</hi> of the Lords <hi>Temporal,</hi> which was a <hi>ſpecial</hi> Caſe.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. 5 <hi>H.</hi> 5. Here the Biſhops had declared Sr. <hi>John Old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle</hi> Heretick, and delivered the Priſoner over to the <hi>Secular</hi> Power; and yet in the Sentence, they may be comprized under the Title of <hi>The most wiſe Lords of this preſent Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="19">19. 2 <hi>H.</hi> 6. It is not <hi>certain</hi> the Biſhops did <hi>Vote.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="20">20. 28 <hi>H.</hi> 6. The <hi>two</hi> Archibiſhops and 13 Biſhops were <hi>preſent,</hi> did <hi>Debate</hi> and <hi>Vote</hi> in the Caſe.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. The Biſhops doubtleſs (as well as in the 28) were <hi>preſent,</hi> being <hi>Peers</hi> of the Realm, as I have proved.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. 38 <hi>H.</hi> 6. The <hi>Commons</hi> did accuſe; the King anſwered, <hi>He would be adviſed;</hi> and ſo the Matter ended.</p>
                  <p>Here we have 22 Precedents cited by this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> from the time of <hi>Clarendon Conſtitutions</hi> to the Trial of the E. of <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> whereof <hi>one</hi> is a <hi>ſpecial</hi> Caſe; <hi>three</hi> are inſignificant and <hi>null,</hi> in regard there was either <hi>nothing</hi> at all done, or a <hi>ſtupid neglect</hi> of their <hi>Right,</hi> or a careleſs throwing off of all <hi>Duty. Four</hi> are doubtful; <hi>Ten</hi> are for their <hi>preſence</hi> at <hi>ſuch</hi> Trials, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>perſon</hi> under the Names and Titles of <hi>Biſhops, Prelates, Peers, Great men,</hi> or <hi>Lords of Parliament;</hi> or preſent <hi>virtually,</hi> by their <hi>Proxies,</hi> or their <hi>Proteſtations;</hi> ſo that there are but <hi>four</hi> of all the 22, for their <hi>not appearing,</hi> or <hi>not voting</hi> at <hi>ſuch</hi> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. For a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> to all further enquiry or diſpute about this matter, we muſt take notice that the <hi>Canon</hi> which requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Biſhops to <hi>withdraw</hi> at all Trials in <hi>Caſes Capital,</hi> is <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd,</hi> and the Lords <hi>Spiritual</hi> are under no obligation to obſerve it. To ſay the <hi>Civil Sanction</hi> does ſtill <hi>enforce</hi> it, is abſurd; for what is that <hi>Civil Sanction</hi> but an <hi>Act of Parliament?</hi> and if an <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament hath <hi>aboliſht</hi> it, it has likewiſe aboliſht all other Acts, which might ſeem to <hi>ratifie</hi> and <hi>confirm</hi> it; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it ſhould be <hi>aboliſht,</hi> and <hi>not aboliſht,</hi> taken away, and yet in force ſtill; which are Contradictions, and abſurd.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Gentleman</hi> takes notice of this to be the Biſhops <hi>Plea, (p.</hi> 67, 68.) <hi>That it is only by the Canon Law that this reſtraint is upon them, and that the forbearance of their Predeceſſors being Papiſts, and ſo ſubject to that Law, was only in that reſpect; which Law being of no force at preſent, and taken away by Act of Parliament, they are now at liberty, though in Modesty they think fit ſometimes to withdraw, but have a Right to continue ſitting if they pleaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What does the <hi>Gentleman</hi> anſwer to <hi>this?</hi> He ſaith, <hi>I do not deny but the Canon Law might give the firſt riſe to ſuch an Uſage; but</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101709:20"/> 
                     <hi>it came afterward to receive a civil Sanction, the ſtamp of Parliament-Authority, and ſeveral confirmations,</hi> ibid. But I have evinced already that his <hi>Allegations</hi> do not prove what he pretends to undertake; and the <hi>practice</hi> of the Biſhops <hi>withdrawing</hi> at ſuch <hi>Trials,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no other <hi>bottom</hi> to relie on than the <hi>Canon Law, That</hi> being abſolutely diſſolved and broken by <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament, cannot now ſupport it.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. And laſtly, Seeing there is no <hi>other</hi> Authority to <hi>continue</hi> and <hi>inure</hi> this practice but that <hi>Popiſh Canon,</hi> I ſhould think it a very dangerous thing (if the King ſhould be ſevere) for any perſon to attempt it; for upon the Clergies <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to the King 25 <hi>H.</hi> 8. 19. the <hi>Statute</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>[Be it therefore now enacted by Authority of this preſent Parliament, according to the ſaid ſubmiſſion and petition of the ſaid Clergy, that they nor any of them, from henceforth ſhall preſume to attempt, alledge, claim or put in ure any Conſtitutions or Ordinances, Provincials or Synodals,</hi> or <hi>any other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, unleſs the ſame Clergy may have the Kings moſt Royal Aſſent and Licence—upon pain of every one of the ſame Clergy, doing contrary to this Act, and being thereof convict, to ſuffer impriſonment, and make fine at the Kings Will.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After <hi>thoſe</hi> Precedents above-mentioned, the next the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi> meets with, was the Earl of <hi>Straffords,</hi> whoſe <hi>Trial</hi> in Parliament was <hi>compleated</hi> in <hi>a Judicial way;</hi> but he was <hi>attaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>condemned</hi> by the <hi>Legiſlative Power,</hi> where this <hi>Gentleman</hi> does acknowledge a <hi>Right</hi> in the Biſhops to be preſent. Why they did <hi>then</hi> withdraw themſelves, ſuch as were not <hi>Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> or <hi>Obſervers</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> times, may beſt learn from Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of them.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, the Author does <hi>proteſt,</hi> that he hath the very ſame <hi>Deſign, Aim,</hi> and <hi>Wiſhes</hi> with that <hi>Gentleman;</hi> for <hi>that Right may prevail is the natural wiſh of every good man.</hi> And the <hi>prevention</hi> of thoſe <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> which the <hi>Enemies</hi> to our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> have <hi>plotted,</hi> and do <hi>atchieve</hi> to put in <hi>execution,</hi> has <hi>incited</hi> me to this task <hi>to ſatisfie my ſelf and others, where the Right is.</hi> My Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents herein <hi>I</hi> humbly <hi>ſubmit</hi> to the <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Honourable Court</hi> of Parliament; and if I have written any thing that gives a <hi>just cauſe of offence</hi> to my <hi>Superiors,</hi> I do here ſolemnly <hi>retract</hi> it.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Gentleman</hi> is <hi>Ingenuous,</hi> and leaves his Reader to his <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> to weigh the Arguments on <hi>both</hi> Sides, and <hi>judge</hi> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. I have taken the <hi>freedom</hi> he allows me, and delivered my Opinion: I pray take you the <hi>ſame</hi> courſe without <hi>Partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and then judge for your ſelf.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
